A big part of how humanity
experiences the universe is visual.
You carry around this device with you
that allows you to capture
what you're seeing in a moment in time,
and then send it
anywhere and everywhere on Earth.
You have this magic piece of glass
that creates
these very transformational experiences
that can teleport you to a place and time.
It's a way of bringing things
that are far away closer.
It's pretty powerful how that's evolved
in a fairly short amount of time
in human history.
I don't think anyone
could've anticipated
how successful Instagram would’ve been.
It's hands down
one of the most influential technologies.
Instagram announcing
that it now has over 400 million...
One billion
monthly active users.
Ian Spalter is a big name here
in Silicon Valley.
One in seven people on the planet
are using a product that Ian oversees.
That's astonishing.
I can't imagine Instagram
without Ian.
His infatuation with craft
let me know that he was going to be
the person to lead design.
The nature of Silicon Valley
is iterating,
is seeing what's next,
is looking at what's new.
Design is everywhere.
There's nothing that you use
that isn't designed in some way.
Their designed to help you complete
a given task.
It's just a matter
of how well designed it is or not.
A design isn't just what it looks like
in a given moment.
It has to do with the entire experience
of using a particular product or service.
The easiest way
to talk about user experience
is in combination with UI.
UI stands for user interface.
Those are just the visual
and physical elements
that a person interacts with
when using a device.
UX stands for user experience.
And that is literally the experience
a person has while using a user interface.
Those feelings can be emotions
like happiness
or frustration and everything in between.
Your stove has a UI.
So what conventions
are out there in the world
that you should take advantage of?
You don't want someone to think
too much about heating a pan.
But then, sometimes
there are opportunities to improve things.
Maybe it's about adding options
that make sense.
So, I have a toaster
that has a button
that says "A bit more" on it.
It literally says, "A bit more."
Totally get why
you would need that, right?
'Cause that's... that's part of
the user experience of making toast.
Now, as a designer, there are costs to
that, because now you added a new button.
Is it worth it? Is it actually valuable?
Is it something that people use,
or is it just sort of superfluous,
you know, and just, like,
maybe sell some toasters.
That's all part of the experience,
thinking about the conditions
and the context.
And then how do you work
within those constraints to make that task
as easy and pleasurable as possible?
- Have a good day.
- See you in a hundred years.
A hundred years?
Instagram is a product used
by a billion people every month,
and we've been around for eight years.
Being at the center
of so many connections and memories
really adds
to the sense of responsibility we have.
Instagram is a social place that you go
to share photos and see photos of friends.
- Hi, everybody.
- Everyone...
Hey, guys. I feel like it's been a while
since I've actually spoken on here.
But I think
that our identities today
are increasingly mediated
through our devices.
And if you're a business,
or if you're a brand,
or you're a celebrity,
a lot of your identity is bound up
with your Instagram.
Instagram's all about showcasing
the things that other people are creating.
And so our job as designers,
in a lot of ways,
is to give them the tools they need
to express themselves
and then get out of the way.
The app isn't just about content,
it's actually about, like,
forming strong relationships with
the people that you're connected to
on the platform
as well as the things
that you're most interested in.
We're pretty rigorous about
thinking through
how I use Instagram
versus how you might use Instagram.
Eugene, do you love us?
Imagine being in charge of
implementing change for a billion people,
including really powerful people.
Like, I can't imagine
the weight that that is.
I think it's important to understand
that this field,
call it product design,
UX design, UI design,
is really young,
and it's also an amalgamation of lots
of things that have come before it.
A computer is a
lifeless, mindless collection of hardware,
but it can be given life of a kind.
In the early days of computing,
you had people
thinking about human factors,
thinking about what it means
for a human to use tools.
Computers were
these giant mainframes.
One K of memory might come in,
like, on a cart with dry ice.
And too, you'd have to hold down,
like, a button
and then tap it with your nose
to, like, make it work, like...
that wasn't... that wasn't hyperbole,
that's just how it was.
People who were designing
the first operating systems,
the first bits of software,
were coming from research backgrounds
with an expertise in human factors.
Trying to understand
people and machines
and what are the different things
you need to consider?
Extensive user tests
have shown that a user
can learn how to use
a Lisa application in 22 minutes.
By simply using the mouse,
the user can move an arrow around
on the screen and simply point.
My father was Jef Raskin,
the guy who created
the Macintosh Project at Apple.
Jef introduced the idea of click and drag,
which now seems so obvious
in retrospect that you would, like,
point to something, click, and move it.
But that as a gesture didn't exist.
You had companies like Apple
trying to bring together liberal arts,
so people who are amazing graphic artists,
like Susan Kare, who could come in
and design icons.
This is a new medium that offers
great control turning off.
There's thousands of little dots in...
And then you kind of fast forward
a bit to, say,
- the early days of the web...
- You've got mail!
And the understanding of what
was expected of designers
was not just media designers
or graphic designers,
but you actually had these titles like
"information architect,"
because the web
was about information,
and you had to think
about how you present that.
Goodbye.
Back in college, the consumer internet
was just getting started.
College campuses were
some of the first places to have access.
So, the way to get access to that was to
go to the computer lab
and stay there as long as possible.
For me, that was staying there
until three o'clock in the morning
on a regular basis,
just playing with stuff
and exploring design.
And so I actually created
my first website.
Both great and awful, I'd say.
Um...
- What was the site for?
- What was it for?
I mean, just to say,
"I know how to build a website," I guess.
- There it is.
- It's pretty awesome. And awful.
Ian Spalter is somebody who
incorporates design
into every level of the business process,
of the creative process,
and the product process.
The work that Ian did on the FuelBand
was a hugely important milestone.
The FuelBand was Nike's take
on the fitness tracker,
and it was arguably
the most compelling take
when it launched in the beginning of 2012.
Nike was interested in
helping everyone become more active.
And it was a project
that was based around a new piece
of hardware that was being developed.
And this hardware was going to be
essentially like a pedometer.
And at this time, pedometers
were like this Scarlet Letter thing.
It wasn't something you wanted to wear.
And so what we wanted to do
is set out to make it fun,
and it would have the Nike stamp on it,
so it would be something
you'd want to wear all the time.
We worked across everything
from thinking about
how you configure this thing and set it up
to the actual visual brand,
what it looked like
from the app standpoint or on the web.
And the FuelBand
was one of the first activity trackers
to implement goal-setting,
individual feedback that would show how
you were progressing towards that goal.
And you get that immediate reward.
One of the things that
Ian and his team were able to do
that nobody else did at the time
was they created a system that allowed
people to improve their habits.
The idea
of tracking your progress
was really within
the domain of elite athletes.
So, Nike Plus was the first time
that the quantified self
really became a mainstream idea.
The FuelBand really helped create
the market that Apple went on to dominate.
The DNA made its way into the Apple Watch,
and it's how people use the devices
in their daily lives.
We had a lot of fun with,
like, making this fun.
Personally, I'm really proud of it
because it's something that
my parents ended up actually using.
And it's something that...
a product they found really valuable
in terms of helping them...
become more healthy.
And also for them to understand
what I actually did every day.
It still works.
Yeah, when ours died, we went out
and got replacements on eBay.
One of the things that
we used to give Ian for his birthday
was just a blank, black bound book
and put the year in.
And he loved it.
So, he used to draw all the time.
And my brother used to say,
"Look at that forehead!
He's gonna be brilliant!"
- "He's gonna be a genius."
- "He's gonna be a genius!" Yeah.
Because he has like a...
We call it a five head, you know?
And so, he was right.
When I start a new project, the
first thing I do is to define the problem,
to understand the "why"
of what we're trying to do
and what is the thing
we're trying to solve for?
Travel back in time a little bit
to around...
I think it was after iOS 7.
Pretty much every application
had flattened out their app icon.
Instagram did not. They wanted to do it
for the right reasons.
Turns out that right reason was me
showing up to actually take it on!
My first reaction was, like, "No!"
But Instagram knew that it had
already evolved from where it started
and it was time to signal
that change was coming.
Ian's first projects
were to redesign the app,
make it more modern,
and redesign our logo.
I want to be really clear on something.
I hated both of these projects.
I didn't want them to happen.
I designed the original logo.
I designed the original app.
He was like, "We're gonna need a room,
and we're gonna need to hole up,
and you're not gonna see anything
from us for three months."
And I'm like, "Can't do that.
We need results. How about a week?"
The first step was
looking at what existed at that moment.
It's this very round shape,
it's got these very candy-like features
in the lens.
And the color is almost brown like...
like a teddy bear or something, you know?
Then on top of the teddy bear,
you got a rainbow.
It's like, what's not to love?
How do you go beyond that?
Where do you...
What's important about this?
What is actually essential?
I remember
they blacked out the windows.
They say that was because
they wanted the mood to be right.
I'm pretty sure they just didn't want me
seeing what they were doing.
So, an exercise I did
was I just had everyone
in our kind of weekly company meeting,
and I said, "All right, everyone,
you have ten seconds
to draw the existing Instagram logo
from memory. Go."
So, everyone kind of...
That, maybe they put the top hat in there.
And then they got the... Whatever, right?
What was interesting
is the range of stuff you got.
And you get some fun things
that look like keyholes,
and, you know, fried eggs.
And, like, a whole range of stuff.
But it was helpful for us as input
to understand, "Wait, actually,
like, this rainbow thing
is starting to pop through in it."
Like, we kind of knew that this top
section was gonna be important.
We knew that the, um... the actual lens
was gonna be important.
But the rainbow popped out
as something that
was really baked into people's memory.
You look at some of our early evolutions,
like, we kind of started here,
just kind of flattening out
the existing app icon.
And we just felt like we were
just creating bootlegs of...
of what existed,
and weren't getting somewhere better.
And then you start to see us getting
back down to basics
and figuring out
what's the actual shape of this thing?
You kind of scan to look for something
that's just interesting,
um, that stays with you,
that looks beyond just, like,
a bunch of shapes thrown together.
This is, like, upside down.
This one's funny.
That's it.
But you make a lot of bad stuff.
And that's just...
That's part of the process.
I remember walking in,
and the walls are just...
plastered with every variant of logo
you could possibly imagine.
We knew that this rainbow bit
was a part of the existing app icon.
And so this idea of having multiple colors
came from that,
and kind of started sampling colors.
Started playing with, "Okay, what if we
don't just go with one solid color?
What if we... What if we
actually start to blend colors?"
I think, at first, I was gravitating
towards this guy,
who was kind of a cute little,
you know, raccoon-looking thing.
When we applied color to it, though,
it also was pretty educational,
because now you've got
these more complicated shapes
on a way more complicated background
and they kind of fight
or just do too much,
where the balance between having
a really simple form
with a lot of color felt better.
I probably remember
everything that happened that day.
I remember being in a dark
conference room at the end of the day
with a bottle of tequila, probably.
I was like, "You guys spent three months
showing me a square in a circle?"
You know?
Then there was...
I think it was an Adweek article.
It was, like,
"The worst design decision ever."
And Ian was like, "It's okay."
You had the world saying one thing,
then your gut telling you something else.
You learn pretty fast
how quick Internet trolls work
when you launch something like this.
There was this gif of, this kid
who was, like... like, has a mullet,
and he's doing stuff on the computer.
And it always ends with him,
like, putting a thumbs up.
And they were kind of jabbing at us
for doing the gradient
as if it was like a simple gradient.
But at the end of that, it stuck.
And can you imagine Instagram
in any other way today?
Talk about change
and people not liking change,
but, in a matter of a few years,
it's gone from
a couple hundred million people
to over a billion.
And that is a huge testament
to the work that he's done there.
So, in addition
to simplifying the app icon,
they also simplified the app itself.
Ian came in
and stripped everything down.
Took out all the color,
made everything a lot simpler-looking.
And the big effect that had
was it made the photos
the center of the user experience.
If I can't go to your app
and in five seconds know what to do,
you've got a big problem.
That's the power of really good UX.
Because computing has become
so much more physical, in a way,
it's like you're actually touching things.
The real world, the physical world,
has gravity.
It has momentum.
And so the expectations of how things
should be able to respond
to you taking actions on these screens,
it's different now.
It's a higher level of expectation.
How should it feel?
What should the feedback be?
How quickly should it move?
There's a lot of these nuances in moments
between the main moments.
You think about any sort of transition
that you see in our app today,
like, maybe it's the cube transition
on stories.
Like, why is that important?
You could have just, like, cut.
When you're watching a film, right,
like, what does that...
Hard cuts versus a... a wipe or a fade,
that kind of changes
the emotional quality of that film.
So getting that feel right is something
that we really place a high premium on.
And so there's a whole team of people
to think about those things
and make decisions to try to make that
as great an experience as possible.
We call our designers
"product designers,"
and the reason why we have
that definition is because
it's not even just about
the user experience.
It's also about
the overall product strategy.
What we are putting out there
is a product.
And so it helps kind of orient people
on what's expected of them.
- And some celebratory moments.
- Yeah.
- Is that something?
- Yeah. We actually have it.
We never want a feature
to feel overwhelming
or look like we spent years on this.
And there's, like, massive features
and so many buttons and...
That's very important to us,
to make sure the app is simple.
This group
is fairly distinctive in that
we don't just think about
frozen moments in time
and, like, layouts.
They're also thinking about how things
move and connect and flow.
A big maze of...
This is...
This is insane, man.
One of the things that I love about
this prototype,
it's really satisfying to watch type...
type in, you know?
- Can you put that on here?
- Yeah. Here.
- Should I put it in?
- I'll just AirDrop it.
Designers here tend to prototype
at very high fidelities,
because it gives us a better idea
of what the end experience is.
We know that you can't really
experience a design
when it's just flat pixels on a screen.
No one, you know, uses products like that.
They use things
that they actually have to tap and use.
Cool. So, today
we're gonna talk about
some of the profile work
that we've kicked off in H-Two,
um, that we're referring to
as "Profile Neue."
We have a team working on Profile.
And Profile is a cornerstone of Instagram.
It's kind of a space of co-ownership
between people making the app
and the actual members of that community.
A profile is the representation
of that person.
And so it's a tricky project
for that reason.
Profile as a surface is starting to break.
When you add new features over time,
things get more complicated
and the design
becomes less and less elegant.
And so we want to take a step back
to make sure that its purpose is clear.
A redesign,
getting it right is very important,
especially if you have a loved product.
You have all these famous examples
throughout social media history
of redesigns and product decisions that
have gone well and that haven't gone well.
Snapchat's redesign did not go well.
Snapchat is facing
a wave of pushback from its users...
complaining the redesign
is confusing and harder to use.
A single tweet
from the reality star
did not help the company's stock.
In the hours
following her tweet,
shares fell
more than six percent Thursday,
wiping out more than
a billion dollars in value.
Some of the problems we see
with Instagram Profile is that
in the past couple years, we've added
a lot more different types of content.
So, we've got story highlights,
stories, IGTV,
different actions for ways to get
a little bit more connected to businesses.
So it's kind of just been a little bit
crowded and everything feels it's, like,
trading off against each other.
Normally, when you do a redesign,
as a designer,
you test it out a lot,
give it to a lot of people.
Like, someone needs
to sit over your shoulder
and watch how you interact.
For the first research study,
we broke down the components of a profile
and we separated them,
to get a very in-depth understanding
of what those individual components
meant to the user.
It needs to be something
that gets embraced by the community.
When you put something out
in the world on Instagram,
people need to eventually like it.
It has to do something better
than what came before.
And so that's going to be challenging.
Whenever I think about
my journey to design,
I think it just comes much more
from a creative and inventive place.
Being interested in sci-fi, Star Wars,
and, more importantly,
how those films were made
and the creativity
that went into inventing something
that didn't exist before,
like what ILM was doing.
I have images in my head right now
of, like, the grainy footage
of scale models, and how they were
set up, and the explosions,
and how they moved the camera.
You're seeing, basically,
the magician's tricks.
You're seeing behind the curtain there.
- Everything's armed, ready to go.
- Okay.
I didn't want to just go out there
and make my own films
and tell my own stories, necessarily.
But there was something about
the mechanics of dreaming that stuff up
and creating this alternate reality.
It was just so captivating to me,
this idea of art and science coming
together to create something magical.
You know, that was true
with, like, ILM and Star Wars,
and I think it was also true
with, Apple.
Thank you for coming.
You're welcome!
We're gonna make
some history together today.
When the iPhone came out,
I think the first notable thing was
the way it had to be described.
- I believe he described it as an iPod...
- an iPod...
- a phone...
and an Internet communications device.
This is one device.
Smartphones up until then,
the face of them had a screen up top,
and the bottom two-thirds were dominated
by this physical QWERTY keyboard.
The iPhone turned the entire front
of the phone into one big screen.
If the entire front of the phone
is one big screen,
how do you interact with it?
You have to touch the screen.
So, you've got highly visual,
highly tactile,
and the combination of those two things
mean that it's also highly adaptable.
It gave third-party developers the chance
to create applications for the phone
that Apple never would have had the time
or the money to come up with on their own.
On the back, the biggest
thing of note is a two-megapixel camera
built right in.
They networked a camera.
That's the fundamental transition
that happened to allow Instagram to exist.
Eventually, they put a GPS chip
in it as well,
and that also unlocked new capabilities.
Actually, a proto version of Instagram
was something called Burbn.
I went around
to venture capitalists and said,
"Hey, I want to build something."
They were like,
"What do you want to build?"
And I said, "Well, get this.
It's a check-in app."
And at the time, everyone
was building check-in apps,
and I was going to build,
like, the 19th version of a check-in app.
Burbn was actually particularly good
at allowing photo uploads,
and that was the thing that actually
people found most interesting.
And before you knew it, Burbn
slowly transformed into what would become
the beginning of Instagram.
They didn't try to do too much.
They picked one thing
and they did it insanely well.
Camera phone photos
were not of great quality at that point.
But by helping people
make small creative decisions,
they were able to create something
that they felt like
was worth putting out into the world.
They added these filters. That
meant they'd wanna share their photos,
because they looked better
and they felt almost like a postcard.
I think we had 25,000 people
sign up on the first day,
and that was more users than I had seen
on any service
that I worked on to that point.
That idea of creativity being born
through constraints is a powerful one,
and it's one that I think Instagram
brought to millions,
then tens of millions,
then hundreds of millions of people.
Facebook snapped up a tiny little company
called Instagram for one billion dollars.
It has just 13 employees.
Tonight, Instagram is worth
12 times more than Kodak.
So, tell me about
this thing called Instagram.
Yeah. Well, I... I knew about Instagram
only as a photo site.
At that time, it was... people were
sharing photos. That's all I knew about it
when Ian moved to Instagram.
And I didn't get the concept.
I don't... I mean, I really didn't.
I really... So, photos? Okay.
You know, I really didn't understand...
how popular it had... it is,
and how popular it has become.
I would say, "I just don't understand
why you would just look at photos
and be, like, ""
- Gets a little... boring after a while.
- And we're old.
And even though I say
I don't look at it that often,
I think I must look at it
about an hour or two a day.
- That's too much!
- Even though I say I don't,
and we say we don't...
we're still on it for, you know,
probably more than we should be.
I didn't travel much as a kid.
And it wasn't until I started working
more professionally,
gettin' thrown out
into these different parts of the world,
that I started to get windows
into these other perspectives.
Like... like, what normal is
in another place.
Maybe it's the flavor of potato chips
in London, right?
Or what a manhole cover
looks like in Japan.
As a designer, you're already tuned
to look at those details.
But then to see how other people
have dealt with that solution
is tremendously inspirational.
It feels like it hacked my brain a bit
to just see reality
from another angle, in a way.
Hai.
I actually went to Japan the first
time with a research trip and I was like,
"What is this?"
When you think about the things we value,
the Instagram design team,
and things I value personally...
around attention to detail and craft,
there's probably very few cultures that
hold that up as high as Japanese culture.
It's a place where all the details
kind of just tickle you.
Everything feels pretty considered.
And you're just soaking all that in.
So, it's stimulating in a different way.
I try to get to the point
where you're just there
and you're actually
just letting it flow through you,
like, what your eyes and ears...
and what you're smelling,
you're able to let that go through you,
that's what you want.
It's less about, "Eureka. I have
this amazing idea about this next thing."
It's, like, no, that's not what you want.
You want it to be able
to flow through you,
and that will create
the space in your mind,
so that when you come back
to those things,
there's more room to breathe and to see
different connections than you saw before.
What are we looking at today?
Profile redesign stuff,
Project Neue again.
Um...
Yeah, so we've been spending time
exploring different directions
and wanted to show you
the breadth of what we've done so far.
- Great, let's do it.
- Cool.
Bar Tab is kind of closer
to what we have today.
So, this is just kind of taking what
we have, this, like, familiar lock-up
and seeing what we can do to kind of make
some of these abilities a little better.
So, Sheety Bio. So, this one is...
what if you literally put content first?
So, this is showing, like,
it actually starts more like a gallery.
Do you guys have anything on device
that we could play with?
Yeah.
- Can I try one of those Sheety ones?
- Yeah.
Making large changes
to a big platform
is always going to be uncomfortable.
And so you have
o just make sure that you are
not making completely emotional decisions.
Yeah.
It's interesting to have
this layered feel to it.
- We also have this B-sides...
- Let's run through 'em.
I'm curious to see how crazy you guys...
- Yeah.
- Go for it.
Um...
It was like... basically, like,
what if your profile was just more like
a story composer
- and you could put what you want anywhere?
- Okay.
- Toss a gif up there.
I don't think this one's
really gonna work,
but we thought it was interesting
to explore.
Yeah, I don't think
this one will work either, but...
but it's important to...
find the edges, right?
You gotta fall off the edge
to know when you've gone too far.
So I'm glad you guys are pushing on it.
There's a bit of
defining the constraints,
understanding what people need.
Like, what are problems in the world
that we are in a position to solve,
that we have the permission to solve?
I didn't go outside a lot as a kid.
Maybe because I was shy or my mom didn't
want me playing with kids in the street,
or I don't know what.
But I was very attracted to computers
and kind of just gravitated to them, like,
if it was in a room,
I just kind of floated over to it.
The first computer that was mine
was a Commodore 64.
♪ Are you keeping up with the Commodore? ♪
♪ 'Cause the Commodore
is keeping up with you ♪
♪ In a world of fun and fantasy ♪
♪ And ever-changing views ♪
This was a birthday gift.
I think it was sixth grade,
and my dad got it for me.
I just remember the moment
of waking up...
and seeing it there, and just being
in awe of it.
I'll never forget that morning.
You had to basically type in
a special code
to load any software.
I still remember the line...
You had to type in "Load,
quote, star, quote,
comma, eight, comma, one."
That's how you... After you put
the floppy disk in!
That's what you had to do
to get anything to work.
And there was something about it
that felt so unique.
It's the possibilities,
you know, of creation
and just seeing that potential
that the thing on screen
could be controlled.
It's not just something being broadcast
to you, but you can actually change that.
Look.
- Man.
- Let me turn the light on.
64K memory.
What actually has mattered a lot
in my career
is not just talent or how hard I work
or anything like that.
It's also about the support
you have from people along your path.
It certainly starts from my parents,
right?
Giving me access to computing early on.
- You wanna try... plug it in?
- Let's see.
Ian gravitated
towards anything technological.
What... Whatever technical issues
anyone had in the building we lived in,
they would come to the door,
knock on the door, "Is Ian home?
We need Ian upstairs.
He's gotta hook up this,
- he's gotta hook up that."
- The cable.
Telephones.
Everybody's knocking on the door,
"Is Ian home? We need help."
I'm of mixed race, right?
So, my dad is white,
he's half-Jewish, half-Sicilian.
My mom's black.
And so I think that's impacted
just who I am as a person.
The fact that I have to think about
what my identity is
as a black person navigating this world.
In terms of the places
that I've chosen to work,
there are not a whole lot of people
that look like me.
When you're a black person
working in these environments,
there can be both a high bar
and a low bar for you.
You're in situations where
people don't expect a lot from you,
but, at the same time, the price
for failure seems very, very high.
Sometimes you can use that as motivation
to go above and beyond, you know,
just to kind of prove something.
Other times it can be kind of crushing,
doubt yourself.
I think that helps build my sense
of empathy for people,
and I think it helps my awareness
of the needs
of people outside of Silicon Valley.
When you're designing products,
you have to think about how people think,
how they approach each other,
how they approach abstract concepts,
like this...
touching on glass.
Seems to be a benefit that
the stories ring is always there.
- Yeah.
- So, you have
this co-mingling, even,
so you can kind of browse through,
you can jump into the story.
- That's kind of a new... dynamic.
- Totally. Totally.
A couple of years ago, I started
listening to Marc Maron's podcast.
And what I appreciated
about the podcast is it got into
different comedians' development processes
and how they put together an act.
Do you write in jokes?
Do you think in jokes?
Well, it's... it's not so much
the writing of the joke,
it's the listening to them bomb,
and then trying to rewrite them.
Listen to enough of these stories
and you hear about how iterative
the process is.
It helped me see points of connection
between what it is that me and my teams
do every day
and what comedians do every day.
Stand-up comedians
are in a position where
they have to come up with ways
to make people laugh.
They may work on the same bit
multiple times a night
in different clubs telling the same joke
a slightly different way,
taking that feedback,
adjusting it until it's tuned.
I don't want to tell you guys
how long she's been single.
But if you take the number of cats she has
and you divide it by the bottles of wine
she drinks a day,
it's 20 years.
She's been single for 20 years.
And so it's really interesting
to have a laugh be a data point,
because that's something emotional.
The laugh is a metric.
And when I bring it back to what we do,
there are plenty of areas in the product
where we try out things
to a limited audience,
and we get back data to understand how
that audience has used a certain feature.
And then we make changes
based off that feedback.
But we don't just look at the numbers.
It's really important
for us to keep our eyes open.
We also talk to people
and we travel all over the world
to understand
how people are using Instagram.
And so it's actually one of my favorite
parts about taking public transportation.
You can look over someone's shoulder
and you see what they're using.
We see unexpected things,
like patterns that they follow.
In the US, we see
a lot of selfies, a lot of text posts.
It's quite different
in a place like Japan.
There, we've seen
a completely different use case.
So, there are less selfies and people
are culturally different
in the way that they share.
It's a product
that people use all the time.
So, how does it fit in with the mix
of other applications
that they may have on their device?
Have they cracked their phone recently?
There's lots of different considerations,
given the scale of computing.
You know, the work he does affects
many, many people, and that's true.
But if I think about that, it scares me.
I wonder if Ian even thinks about it.
Does he... Does he think about it?
That's a lot.
That's a lot of people.
Interaction design, at its core,
is a psychological exercise.
If you've ever been scrolling through
your Twitter feed or your Instagram feed,
you've noticed you don't hit the bottom.
That's a relatively new feature,
called bottomless scroll.
And that was invented
by a designer named Aza Raskin.
Which I feel like
I have to forever atone for.
When I was thinking about infinite scroll,
like, the thought was...
I, as a designer, have failed
if I ask the user to make a choice
they don't care about.
So, scrolling already means "I haven't
seen what I want, show me more."
So, why bother having, like,
little buttons at the bottom
that you click to show... show more?
I as an individual designer
doing human-computer interaction,
like, will happily make
an infinite scroll.
But if I'm thinking at this higher level,
I would have known that
that would remove the stopping cues,
just like when I'm drinking
a glass of wine.
I stop drinking when I finish my glass,
and I think, "Do I want more?"
Here, we're not giving people
the stopping cue.
And so it's literally wasted
hundreds of millions of human hours.
It's no longer enough as a designer
to think about the constraints
of just one individual
using my product.
Instead, we have to think
the fractal version up
to technology-society interaction.
We haven't really fledged that out
as a field yet.
And now we're seeing that our technology
not only distracts us,
but if you think about what Facebook does,
they build a little simulator of you.
They build one of these little simulators
for one-fourth
of the human beings on Earth.
You are the product.
You don't get the service for free.
You are handing over your data.
You are being targeted.
This business model,
especially with Facebook, led to...
the proliferation of fake news.
It led to misinformation
being spread out there.
You know, there's a fine line
between micro-targeting, manipulation.
It's also allowing us to compare
our fake, fabulous lives
to other people's fake, fabulous lives.
I think that can be problematic
for a lot of us.
Because Facebook owns Instagram now,
there's been, I think,
more pressure on Instagram.
And especially now with the pressure
to make money,
especially with the pressure now
of Facebook not doing as well as it was,
and Instagram kind of being,
like, this golden child.
I think the challenge for Instagram
is going to be staying Instagram.
I think the focus on people
and human needs
has been something throughout my work.
Not just communicating a message,
but you're also trying to connect
with a human need or desire,
something core to you,
who they are as people.
All right, what's this one about?
So, this is a couple
of different things.
The first thing we wanted to dig into
is this problem that we heard a lot about,
vanity metrics.
When we talked to people
about their profile,
we got feedback
that they didn't necessarily like
the numbers at the top
of the profile that said
how many followers you have,
and how many people are you following,
because they felt
some sort of social pressure.
So right now, with the current design, um,
the metrics that we have,
the follower and following count,
is prominent, right up at the top.
- Yes.
- And that causes a lot of anxiety
in terms of popularity,
having a lot of friends
and their self-worth.
And so by placing the metrics
a little bit down below,
we're kind of humanizing it
and dulling down that anxious experience
of the ratios next to each other.
So, it would be a big step to,
like, downgrade overall followers.
Do you feel like that's...
That's a net good thing?
That's actually
our biggest concern
with the launch of the redesign.
This is probably the most sensitive thing.
That's like a drop-the-mic move, isn't it?
I interviewed one of the founders
of Twitter recently,
and his biggest regret, he said, was
putting your follower count on Twitter.
I was like, "Why?"
And he said, "It just put us down
a weird path. Like, incentive."
Like, you know, when it talks about
incentivizing people
to post for likes, or post for followers.
I mean, I think that tension
keeps me up at night, honestly.
The benefit that we have
is we can set those principles
and make them really clear to people.
The pace of change
in the past 20 years
has been pretty tremendous when it comes
to communication technologies.
But we also know it's just the beginning.
So, I think it's going to be important
to have a clear point of view
on where we want these tools to take us.
At the core, Instagram
is about visual communication.
So I feel like that's something
that there will always be space for,
that we're well-positioned
to continue to plan.
How close are we to be building out...
this version, or some version of this,
for any sort of first test?
Yeah, we're actually able
to phase these different tests out to see
how it affects the ecosystem soon.
So, we took out the Sheety Bio,
as well as the Card Shark and the Bar Tab.
And what we found was
that the Bar Tab was most favorable.
Only because it was not too different
from what they're normally used to seeing,
and it really helped them
better understand the profile
compared to their existing experience.
The design we ended up
moving forward with
and evolving from is called "Bar Tab."
We've moved the profile photo
and increased the size of it.
We've changed the prioritization
of the metrics
that currently exist in the profile
and made that a little bit less important.
We've made the descriptive copy
that people put in on their profile
more important.
And then we've also evolved
and created a new system for buttons.
A little more than a coat of paint,
you know, but not a full, like,
renovation down to the studs.
But, you know, design is never done.
It's something
that will continue to evolve.
The first launch
may be just the first step.
I've really benefited
from working in this space
and seeing these technologies evolve.
It's given me a tremendous perspective.
These tools are certainly transforming us,
and we don't yet know
where they're going to take us.
How many you going for?
- Five.
- Five? All right, we'll do five.
All right, ready?
Here you go. Ready? Give me one.
Good. Two.
For my kids,
I think the one thing that is certain
is that things will be uncertain.
I think that their ability to deal
with change will be pretty critical
to how they are able to survive as people.
Up, up, up, up, up, up, up, up, up!
Right now, my kids don't have
phones still, even my 12-year-old,
and he actually has been explicit
about saying,
“I actually don't think I want one.”
Maybe this is a part of us working through
what it is to have these devices.
There's nothing that says
that we can't come up with
these new kind of expectations
and social standards.
We are inundated with so much information
that you need to give yourself the space
to experience the world
in an unmediated way.
To just be in a place
and use your natural given senses,
no tools.
It actually clears out a lot of the noise
and gives me the capacity
to either be creative
or be a better dad or a better husband
or a better boss.
The ability to zoom out for a minute
and get that clarity of perspective,
it's one of the best things
that we're able to do.