When I design toys,
I want children to create
from their imaginations
rather than following instructions.
If I were to give kids a set of parts
and tell them to build a car...
there would be
a right and a wrong answer.
They already have an understanding
and archetype of what a car is.
It's a finished idea.
On the other hand, if I give them
the parts and pieces and say,
"Build a way to get to school,"
then there's room for many ideas.
And they could make a sidewalk,
or a rocket launcher,
or a bird saddle.
My work as a designer
is to give them these tools,
so that they are free to imagine,
explore ideas, and invent new things.
I wouldn't say
that I design toys per se.
There's a connotation with the word "toy,"
which is kind of frivolous.
And so I say that I design for play.
Which is kind of weird because it sounds
like I'm saying "designing foreplay."
So, it's not a perfect title...
but it's different
than designing play, right?
We don't design the play,
we design for the circumstances
of play to arise.
I have a hard time distinguishing
play from design.
In a way, a lot of what we do
in design is play.
Testing things out as ideas, as concepts,
but also as objects in space,
we’ll play with things.
I like to start
with kind of an experiential goal
and then design the object or the system
or the playground or whatever it is,
design that around it.
I've been working on something
called The Critter,
which is in the early phases.
I saw an old pommel horse
and they're so beautiful
and they're such an interesting
kind of abstraction of a horse.
And I remembered
that I loved playing on that.
And then I started looking
more at ride-on toys,
so some other old ones
that you might crank
to make it move forward.
And just kind of some simple versions.
The Critter has holes in it
and things plug in,
so if they want it to have wheels,
it can have wheels.
If they want it to have a rocker,
it can have rocking legs
that would plug in.
And then whatever
other kinds of, maybe, feet
or things that spin.
So, it can be a creature or a vehicle
or an invention of their own, hopefully.
All along the roofline in her studio
are sketch after sketch after sketch
that are stapled, taped, pinned.
Every time I go,
there's different sketches
and, you know, the next thing
she's thinking about.
I think of sketching
as an extension of my brain.
Like, I have an idea
and can't really figure it out
until my hand is helping.
So, sometimes I have an idea
of what it is in my head, but it's usually
not finished until I get it on paper.
I don't find words as useful as images.
So, in communicating it to other people,
I always manage to come at things
from a completely different direction.
So, when I worked
for a bigger design firm,
I would get called in to meetings
to be the wildcard.
Cas is a designer,
but she's, like, kind of
off the normal professional way.
She's like a kid
and so happy and excited about stuff
that it makes everything
that she's doing fun.
When I was working
with Rockwell Group,
David Rockwell had started the momentum
of a kind of a pet project of his interest
of reinventing the playground.
I wound up on that project,
which was a dream.
When I was first put on that project,
I was just sketching
different forms of playground.
How can we make
a playground look different?
Beautiful sculptural things
and different ways of holding up a slide.
But I could tell it looked different,
but the play was the same.
So, I started doing this thing.
I would draw a child
in different positions
and then sketch a way to get them there.
So, the slide is adrenaline
and quick, uncontrolled movement.
How else can I facilitate that?
Ultimately, the design of the...
Now, they're kind of called
the Big Blue Blocks.
They're based on
the Caroline Pratt Unit Blocks,
the most basic modular building blocks.
They're just giant.
And we designed a way
for children to build and create
a playground that would change
and evolve throughout the day.
So, the Big Blue Blocks came out of
the idea of an ever-evolving playground
that's designed by children.
We tend to
downplay play, as if it's...
that frivolous, joyful thing that
children do, but it's really their world.
It's like the water that they swim in.
And so free play, where there's not
a right or wrong answer,
gives them this sense of
"I can do it, I can think for myself."
In psychology, we call it agency
or, you know, confidence.
But it's that idea
that the child really feels like,
"Hey, I had an idea, and I did it."
And that then spurs on learning.
I remember as a kid,
I began to learn
that our constructed environments
were places that enforced
certain hierarchies and power structures
that were not friendly to everybody,
particularly children.
And I have a few really specific memories
of being so mad about the height of sinks.
The height of sinks
I just thought made no sense.
I was aware
that they were not designed for me.
I just knew this is totally stupid
and adults are ridiculous
and these sinks are such a stupid height.
You know, 'cause I was like,
"An adult could use a low sink,
but children can't use a high sink.
Like, this isn't a hard problem to solve,
people. Come on, get with it."
I want my designs to speak to the weirdos.
Like, I don't know how else to say it.
But I want them to be tools
for children to feel understood.
My first product was called Geemo.
At the time, I was looking at a lot
of different patterns in nature,
and with Geemo, specifically bone marrow.
And so I was thinking about how one unit
can make an irregular pattern.
Geemo is on a three-pointed grid,
but the center is off.
Like, I scooted the center a little bit.
And so I made a whole series
of different parts and pieces with limbs,
figuring something out where it would join
and become all one piece.
And then the magnetic ends,
that was very specific
to it becoming a more open-ended toy
because I thought about
making them different colors,
that positive might be one color
and negative might be another,
so they match up.
But there's something,
I think, wonderful about
when the magnets don't meet.
And if it had the instructions
built into it through color coding,
you would figure that out and then never
do it wrong and never have that moment.
I worked with one company
that was gonna bring it into production
and kind of at the last minute, they said,
"Okay, so what are the characters?
What are the faces?"
And I was like,
"Wait, what? What do you mean?"
And they were like,
"Well, you know, obviously, the face."
And I just said, "Wait, what? How..."
Like, they had been making
an assumption about...
that this wasn't finished, that I was
going to put some kind of face on it.
And I was like, "Wait, no.
No, that's not that... What?"
I decided not to work
with them after that.
People say, "Well, does it...
But kids like colors!"
And I'm like,
"Kids are actually pretty sophisticated.
Like, they can play with a white toy
and appreciate that
the color isn't telling them what it is."
It won an award.
So, it launched in the New York
MoMA Design Store in 2006.
And...
I had a couple chances to license
the idea to another company,
but I was... young,
naive, and arrogant.
So, I said, "I'll just...
I want to do this myself."
Which, trial by fire.
I learned so much
and it took years and a lot of money.
And there were times that Geemo
had a studio and a place to live,
but I did not.
The running of that part of the business,
it was all I was doing.
And I realized that,
you know, what I wanted to be doing
was designing more toys.
My company is called Heroes Will Rise,
and I launched it in 2006.
Essentially, we tried to design it
such that there are...
In and of itself, it's modular
for the manufacturing.
So this is a scale model
just with foam core of this one.
- Three and a half?
- Three and a half.
I no longer have to live on couches,
which is nice.
I'm no longer doing it alone.
I have an incredible business manager
named Doug Johnson,
who was a game-changer.
The motto and kind of the driving force
is "easy is boring."
"Easy" meaning something
that doesn't engage your thinking.
There's an assumption
in the field of design
that easy is great, right?
"My God, I have to push three buttons,
that's a problem.
I should just have to push one button."
And I'm not quite sure
why that's a good thing.
When I was in Japan, I became familiar
with this partnership,
Arakawa, he was an architect,
and Madeline Gins, who was a poet.
And Arakawa and Gins
had a kind of a thinking group
that was called
Architecture Against Death.
And the core of their ideas was that
if life is predictable, you're a zombie.
So the Architecture Against Death
was about, "Why do floors need to be flat?
What if you had to pay attention
while you walk?"
You know, "Why do we have
rectilinear corners?"
So the idea is that you should be aware
and be paying attention,
and that's how you stay young
and continue thinking.
I kind of, like, was poking around
and realizing...
"Right, we kind of have, like...
Toys are kind of crap."
They're plastic. They're, like...
They're not... They're just...
They're... They're not something
kids are getting something out of.
Mama!
I started to feel like they were
designed to keep kids occupied...
or they were designed to sell.
But they weren't really designed
with children and play value in mind.
Lots of toys are very goal oriented.
They look like something,
there's one way to play with it.
So, you quickly figure out it can go
this way or that way and then you're done.
So it sort of shuts down
that building on their own
pleasure and engagement and enjoyment.
You see Rigamajig being used
by a group of kids
and you get it.
You have an emotional understanding of it.
Rigamajig is a kit of parts
that could be seen as a learning material.
It could be seen as a toy or a playground.
I think of it as a glorified pile
of construction debris.
There are so many parts and pieces to it.
It has planks, nuts and bolts,
some corner brackets,
hooks, and there's a pulley.
What I did in designing it,
I wanted children to be able
to build without mastering a tool.
So, I wanted it to be
intuitive and usable for small hands.
I took the... kind of a wingnut,
and I took the wings off of the nut
and put it on the bolt,
so the bolt and the nut
can easily be screwed in
and actually get pretty tight
without using any kind of tool.
And those are intentionally black.
They are meant to look like real hardware.
The boards are three-quarter-inch plywood.
They're heavy planks. You know,
it's a very large, heavy piece of wood.
Children really often when they first
encounter Rigamajig say, "This is real."
You can see them kind of like,
"Okay," you know.
And they play with it differently,
and they know that they can impact space
and that they can make something
larger than themselves,
and being entrusted
with real materials
is also hugely empowering for them.
Originally, Rigamajig was part
of a commission
by the Friends of The High Line
in New York City.
It was
the High Line Children's Workyard Kit.
And was just so successful,
and I got such great feedback,
specifically from teachers,
saying, "This is wonderful.
I want to use this in the classroom."
I tried to sell it
to some other companies.
They were like, "This is too weird."
I started to bring it to the market
on my own.
The first time I showed it,
I was pretty discouraged.
The feedback was like,
"Where does it even fit in?"
You know, it's really hard
trying to put it into one of the boxes
in the industry, 'cause there's really
nothing else out there like it.
I'd like to see a lot more of it,
personally,
'cause things do seem
too repetitive and prescribed.
And I think kids
want the more open-ended,
and I think they need more open-ended.
You know, they get taught
enough instructions.
If we manufactured
our children in a child factory,
they'd all be alike.
Then we could teach them very easily.
I've always been interested in,
"How can school be different?
Why does school have to look like that?"
Elementary schoolroom USA.
It's a wonderful part
of the American scene.
It's commonplace, but important.
And it's quite the same
whether it's in a big city,
average town, or country hamlet.
The rows of desks,
there's an expert at the front.
The assumption that,
like, we're just an empty sponge
and the teacher
is the vessel of knowledge.
"I'm gonna tell you a bunch of stuff,
and now it's in your brain
and now you know it."
We're still using a model that was
developed around industrialization.
It was developed
to make factory workers.
I figured this out pretty early on
that in school,
what I was being assessed on
was how good at school I was.
And then we reinforce this with SATs
and things like this.
But this is not a gauge of intelligence.
It's a gauge of how well you take tests.
School was hard.
Like, when I saw my peers doing well,
I just was like,
"All right, I guess
they're just smarter than me."
And I think the things that I'm good at
weren't celebrated
and they weren't seen
as something that was smart.
And it just didn't make sense to me
that we were spending
our childhood indoors.
Classroom should be about
the world that's outside,
not its own weird tomb
of archaic knowledge.
Working with design students and designing
for children or early education,
it all starts to feel
like it's all the same thing,
and I think that my teaching
with undergraduate art students
is more influenced by
what I know and have understood about
early education than vice versa.
Let's start over here.
We're not critiquing a final piece.
We're testing, so I think
it's up to the artist what...
Think about what you want to learn, right?
Or what you're curious about.
Be strategic about what you tell us.
Right?
In the classroom,
we play constantly.
So, the longest part
is the cylinder that goes up,
and then this is the most confusing shape,
'cause I don't know the name for it.
It's like a cylinder
has been carved into it.
- Is this your object?
- Hey!
This is the object.
My first year of teaching, I had
the Introduction to Design students.
I had so much fun
designing these exercises
and these assignments for them.
We were calling it Name By Function.
So instead of saying,
"Let's all design a mug,"
it's like, “Design a way
to transport water.”
So, you know, they'll have them sketch
ten ways to transport water
not found in the kitchen.
Okay, so there's a hose...
The really great thinkers will say, "Okay,
you know, my hands cupped together
is a way of transporting water."
"My mouth." "A sponge."
And then I'll say,
"Okay, now sketch ten more."
It's a fun exercise to do
with beginning design students
who thought that they were going to come
to school and design shoes and cars.
And I'm like, "No! Let's have
an existential crisis instead."
Growing up, we lived in the woods
in Grass Valley, California,
near the Yuba River.
It's all just gorgeous, hot rocks.
I was almost always outside.
And so,
I think I understand,
through my own experience,
the value and the joy
and the importance of play.
And particularly of free play.
I was raised by a single parent.
My mom worked a lot.
So, I mostly played alone. I was what
would be considered a latchkey kid,
but the house didn't have keys,
so that never fit.
People would say, "You're a latchkey kid."
I was like, "No, I don't have a key."
Real literal about it.
And it's hard
when I think about her when somebody says,
you know, "What did you do?
What was your play?" And I'm like, "..."
That's... It was play, so it was noth...
Like, I don't...
I don't know, I was outside doing, like...
Poking a dead thing with a stick.
Like... It's this... Climbing a tree.
I don't know what I did up there,
but I was doing it for three hours.
Like, that's also the point of play
is that there's not an outcome
other than that it's intuitive.
I made a mark here
about where ten was.
Ten yards.
So are you going to shoot after I shoot?
- Yeah.
- Good.
- It's such a satisfying sound.
- Okay. It is, isn't it?
I always wanted my kids
to take their curiosity
just as far as it would go.
You know? So, I always encouraged that.
Wow.
I think I almost held the thing still
at that point.
- Good.
- No finger...
When she was young,
our property had been cleared
of a lot of manzanita,
but they'd never been really dug up,
so there's all these
little manzanita stumps all over the yard.
And she would go out there barefoot,
and she would always be hurting herself
and stubbing her toes.
And so she told me
that I needed to go out there
and clear the yard.
And I said, "Well, why don't you put on
some shoes when you go out there?"
"I can't be bothered with shoes.
I'm too busy playing."
So, that was her attitude.
Here's attitude right here.
I didn't worry too much.
You know, we always made sure that when...
before they jumped off a rock,
they knew they needed to check
the depth of the water
and what they were jumping into
type thing.
But as far as what their actual choices
to do in that space,
I... I didn't really worry too much.
This would be the mom section.
And this is the Cas section.
I think that all humans play
because we have to.
Increasingly,
we're starting to understand
how much animals play, not just to learn.
We know that children and animals
will play as a way of learning.
Bears play fight,
and that's kinda how they're learning
to actually fight.
But they also play for enjoyment.
This is the beauty of YouTube.
We can now watch videos of crows
using a yogurt lid to slide down a roof
that has snow on it
and then climb back up and slide down
again for no purpose other than play
and the enjoyment of the act.
Play is as essential as food, air, sleep,
whatever else we have to do to stay alive.
Play is therapy. It engages our brain,
it gets our body and our mind
back in tune with each other.
As kids, we lose some of the inhibition
that happens on a playground,
but it translates into different places
in our lives, I think.
Moving our bodies around, whether
it's in some kind of sport or exercise
or, for me,
dance has more of a flow to it.
Dancing is more than
part of my inspiration process.
I think dancing is part of
my "being a sane human" process.
I enjoy dancing quite a bit,
and I'm a very good breakdancer.
I came up with this persona
when I was living in San Francisco,
a fellow named Electro,
the Pop and Lock King.
And I was doing drag
at a club called Tranny Shack.
And really amazing, active, creative
performance art, drag scene.
In the meantime,
I was trying to pretend to be
a person who could work in an office.
At the time, The Maury Povich Show
was doing these pageants.
"Is it a man or a woman?"
While the audience shouted,
"It's a man! It's a woman!"
She's a man, baby! Yeah!
Which is so beyond messy now,
and I kind...
I knew that at the time also,
but I'd never been to New York.
And I said, "So...
is it okay if I take this day off
to fly to New York
to be on The Maury Povich Show?"
Flip to two months later
when the show aired,
they shut down the entire office,
and we all piled into the conference room
to watch it on TV.
So, Electro, come on out!
Which was...
Well, it was mortifying.
But it was also amazing, because here
were these people being super supportive
and embracing that side of me,
which I thought
had previously been kind of secret.
Moments like that where I'd realize
I didn't have to separate my selves.
I think half of the reason
that I liked performing
was making all of the costumes
and the sets.
And I started doing more, like,
"Why don't I do, like, Pegasus drag?
Or hot dog drag?" So, my costumes
were getting more elaborate.
That a little bit
fulfilled the creativity,
but I always had some version
of a studio where I was making
other things on the side.
I was making furniture and these kind of...
elaborately fabricated
cast epoxy toilet seats.
But they sold in galleries.
They were 400-dollar toilet seats.
But it was really important to me
that people put them on their toilets.
That was the first thing that I considered
putting into mass production.
And then I realized
that epoxy goes nowhere.
It'll be here for so many thousands
of years after I am dead.
We're burning through
non-sustainable objects faster and faster.
So, I'm very careful
about what I put into the world.
So, with Critter,
the stage we are at now is
I'm starting to develop it
and thinking about materials,
and have talked to
a couple of different companies
about how they might
want to develop and market it.
I imagine it'll be a combination
of different materials:
wood and some kind of
soft plush sorts of things,
as well as some probably rigid components.
And then for the plug-ins, or the doodads,
as I've been calling them,
these are more of a sketch model.
They're just, like, whatever cardboard
I had laying around,
um, hot glue and tape
to hold things together.
So, really quick ways to figure out
how they'll work.
Like, this can be both a robot claw
and a foot and maybe a moon.
Any toy could be
turned into a non-open-ended toy.
The way I see it working against the child
is that it says to them,
"Either you do it right
or you do it wrong."
If you feel like you're not good
at something, you just retreat.
Children are curious.
They want to engage with the world,
and you give them open-ended toys,
they're much happier.
- This is one-third scale model.
- Right.
And this is a three-year-old.
I'll take the prototype
and give it to kids,
teachers, parents,
whoever would have some expertise,
and, of course,
they always have really helpful input.
From a three-year-old's
point of view...
- I hadn't thought about that.
- Well, you can peek in.
- Yeah. Yeah.
- And children like to see or peek.
You know, "Are my things in there?"
Plus, I can open it and peek.
I didn't think about that, which
could be really fun with color, right?
- If the things inside of it...
- Are colored.
Like, somehow...
- Or if even the insides of the...
- Even if...
That's what I was thinking.
Or even if the inside of this has color.
- Yeah.
- So they can...
Like, if this were...
Right. We could kind of color
- the insides of the...
- Yeah.
When I saw it, I thought,
"Mailbox or birdhouse?"
But the more we talked about it,
the more I could see,
“There's so many possibilities
with it."
It's that it says a child could take this
and do whatever they want with it.
Says to the child,
"Your ideas are really important." Right?
'Cause if you've created something
and it was your ideas and now
you carried them out, then it's yours.
Here's a child activist mobile.
It's a megaphone.
Design is kind of my tool
for activism, in a way.
I find myself in big box stores.
There's, like, the pink aisle
and the blue aisle. It's infuriating.
It makes no sense.
There are children who like pink
and children who like blue.
Why we've assigned that
to boys and girls is absurd.
It's just not how children... are,
or it is how they wind up being,
because that's what...
the options that they're given.
Introducing the new
GI Joe Adventure Team.
Five rugged men with lifelike hair.
She changed it ten times,
and she wants it curly again.
Better fix Ken a sandwich.
It's important to me
to have some positive impact,
in particular, when I see things
that I struggled with in childhood
that I don't think were necessary.
I probably started having
an awareness of gender,
it was maybe around third grade.
I knew that, you know, there were
boys and girls and I was a girl.
But there was a point
at which I was meant to stop...
To start... Well, stop being a tomboy.
Simultaneously,
my dad was not happy with me
not growing out of a tomboy.
And he was in charge of a lot of
the back-to-school shopping.
He caught me sneaking over
into the boys' section to get the clothes
to bring them into the girls' section.
I thought he wouldn't figure that out.
And then he just was
not going to buy me clothes.
I needed to get over it.
I needed to grow up.
And so that was the first time that
I realized it was going to be an issue.
Then I started, I think,
noticing in other places
where men and women
were treated differently
and that the expectations were starting
to get really inconvenient.
It felt like there was
a set of rules that
if the other girls didn't follow,
those wouldn't be expected of me.
So, I was, like, a little bit mad
and disappointed
at them for following the rules
of wearing dresses
and screaming
when you see a worm.
But I think it's always been
a huge presence.
It's a lens through which I have no choice
but to see the world.
And did your dad,
like... What happened there?
No, he never came around. He's still mad.
No. It's, um... I mean,
if only that were our only issue.
I think...
the fact that I'm a feminist
and my gender is a bigger issue for him
than the fact that I'm queer.
I...
don't need to psychoanalyze him,
but we don't talk.
We haven't... We periodically would go
a year, a couple years without speaking...
Um, but I was recently
officially disowned.
At this point,
we're, like, going on 25 years of therapy.
So, I can live without a relationship
that just makes me feel crappy.
I didn't know that Alesdair was...
something that I could have,
let alone even want to have.
I understood vaguely
when people talked about
their primary person and love
and true love and whatnot.
And, of course, I've had many versions
of lots and lots of love.
Um... but this one's
pretty stinking good.
Yeah.
She invited me to this party
after a month had gone by,
and I thought, "What do I have to lose?"
And I immediately came in
and she took a blowtorch,
- and was like...
- I was trying to impress him.
"Let me show you the bubbles in the pond."
And so she comes out with the blowtorch
and just starts blowtorching the frozen...
brook, being like, "Isn't this cool?"
- And, to be fair, it was pretty cool.
- It was cool.
After I came out to you...
the initial conversation was...
was hard and didn't go well and...
You know...
It probably felt for a while
that it was gonna be something
that was not gonna be forever.
I'm like, "Really?"
You didn't think I was gonna stick?
So specifically this one didn't...
That I was going to grow out of it,
and, like, how could you...
Really, Mom? At some point,
you called me up out of the blue
and you said, "I was just watching
the news and in Sacramento..."
And I remember you saying
it was a gay protest, and I was like,
"We call those Gay Pride parades."
And you said, "But there was a woman
carrying a sign that said,
‘I love and support...’"
It said, "I love and support
my lesbian daughter."
And you said, "And I realized that,
of course, I love, but I haven't really
supported you as a lesbian daughter."
I remember this conversation.
And you apologized, and, um...
I was... That was...
It felt like a big moment.
Yeah.
And it made my life much easier,
in fact.
As I've been able to...
have more control over being in places
and being surrounded by people
that are supportive of who I am
and who I can contribute
to a community of people
who support and love each other...
I have less and less tolerance
for places that aren't like that.
Come here.
In my mind, I want...
every... Like, I want language,
I want gender, I want all of those things
to work like a basic building block.
A basic building block, that can be
a car or a whale or a hat.
To have the malleability
that that has as kind of a placeholder
for our imagination to kind of build from.
So, who can tell me what, um...
what an inventor is? What's an inventor?
The reason that I design
for children is I'm designing for people.
These are the people that are gonna,
like, make the world suck
or not suck. Right?
Good toys make good people.
And I really believe in that.
Who's got a question...
Who's got a question for Cas?
What gave you the idea
of making Rigamajigs?
Well, I noticed
and I know that you all are capable
of building things
that are big and exciting,
and that you have ideas
of what you want to build
in such a way that you would get to choose
what you were making
rather than me telling you what to make.
Rigamajig has been on the market now
for five years.
It translated more
to being in the classroom
to teach curricular needs.
But also collaboration.
There's a lot of collaborative
opportunities with materials that big.
It's designed in such a way
that children need each other.
You have to get somebody to hold this end
while you're screwing in
the bracket that's over there.
Well, they don't know
what's going to come out of it,
because hopefully, in its best case,
it's open-ended.
So, nobody knows
what the children are gonna build.
Nobody knows what kind of interpersonal
dynamics are gonna come out,
nobody knows where it might go.
Of course, the children, I don't think,
experience that as vulnerability.
I think, for the kids,
that's all just play, it's all unfolding.
My biggest challenges
are other people's perceived rules.
Our overarching perception of risk
and what is an acceptable level of risk
for children in play.
It's hard to remember
that those are not real.
Children can have a big heavy board
and not get hurt.
What do we say to Cas
for inventing Rigamajig?
Thank you!
Thank you for playing,
and thank you so much for sharing with us.
Prior to the Fast Company article,
I think Cas was a little-known secret.
Mostly through social media,
all of a sudden, she became known.
Rigamajig became known.
And so we had people contacting us
that we had never done outreach to.
A couple years ago,
someone contacted me and said...
"I've seen your stuff
in use in China.
It's a region of schools that I work with.
They have a couple of prototypes
of something similar to Rigamajig.
Basically, long story short,
you're being knocked off in China.
But not by us,
'cause we'd like to work with you."
And so, my...
my first instinct, hearing that Rigamajig
was being used in some schools there,
I thought, "That's much better than
whatever stereotype
of Chinese schools I had."
Then I also thought, “Well, let me see
what they've done with it,
because I'm sure they've changed it
slightly, and maybe they improved it.”
And she just started showing me
these images of what they call Anji Play.
Kids building elaborate structures
and leaping off of barrels.
And I was speechless.
At that point,
I had been working for over a decade
in playground design and material design.
And, to some extent,
like, I had kind of stopped trying
to do something that ideal.
I knew it was possible that children
could do all those things.
I didn't know it was possible to let them,
because of rules and liability.
The idea that Rigamajig was being
knocked off was really disappointing.
And Doug, my business manager, was like,
"We have to stop them."
But the person who was making it
was different than the person
who was buying it.
And so we realized that
we could be chasing patent infringers
or we could try to partner
with the schools.
How's it going?
Yeah?
You're regrouping to go play?
Okay!
After you, my friends.
Very quickly, I went to China
and I learned that
in this region, there were 120 schools
and 14,000 children using this model.
They're outside for two hours a day,
they have these incredible assortment
of materials...
building with these giant blocks,
leaping off of ladders.
They decide what they're playing with,
they bring it out, they put it away.
The teachers
are really brilliant observers.
I shifted from
the initial protective shock,
and I immediately knew that I needed to
be involved and learn from what
Ms. Cheng was doing in Anji Play.
Ms. Cheng, she's the founder
and had kind of been developing Anji Play
over the course of 16 years.
And Ms. Cheng is... is a genius.
When talking about the relationship
between designers and children,
we had a lot in common.
So, we felt like old friends.
So, we asked Cas
to help us
with standardization of Anji Play.
We have been working
to bring Anji Play to the US
and the rest of the world.
I suppose, to some extent,
I'm the design director.
Today, Ms. Cheng pointed out
that the children love
playing with things that are off-balance.
And so, I'm thinking about some new ways
that some of the materials or things
could be compatible
with the larger system,
and bring in ways that they can
experiment with balance more.
The unstable...
I saw children put the A-frame
or the double ladder
onto one of the barrels.
Yep. Would it be good if the slats
went all the way through?
The same way that it might line up
with the climbing cubes?
- ‘Cause that... that would be...
- Yeah.
Also, a funny kind of...
I would imagine if it's going this way...
And this would be... Actually,
this would be a good teeter-totter.
The driving ethos
is what we're curious about.
And that's such a big shift
from "What did you learn?"
Right? That there's an outcome,
that there's a thing
that is to be learned,
that we know what can be learned,
and therefore you're out to look for it.
I was watching these girls,
this tire course,
and they pull the tire up there,
and then they roll it down the plank,
and it goes through the... the tube
and then lands into the cube.
And as soon as it got in,
then, of course, like,
what's the point? So, then they keep
making it more and more complicated.
'Cause easy is boring.
I do have hope that if you show schools
where this really, really works
and then you get another school to try it
and another school to try it,
that you can get
this kind of contagion effect.
Because you see it in the children.
You see their joy, you see them learning,
you see them growing.
It's not just about children,
that's truly about humanity.
So...
I'm going to be hopeful that we can get,
like, a little bit going,
and, you know, a little bit
can add to a little more of Anji.
I think that design is critical
to our future, and the world.
And all of my designs,
whether it's Rigamajig
and the occasional playground design
and project that I do,
Geemo and then with Anji Play,
all of them are about empowering
thinking outside of the archetype.
I saw it as an opportunity
to have an impact on the future.
I don't... It's funny.
I don't... It's not that I like kids.
I don't dislike kids. I like people.
I am...
I’m sure I'm going to get
some pushback from that, but it's true.
And so, in my mind...
if we can give kids the tools
to build confidence
and have agency and understand
how to be creative, empathetic,
good people, then I thoroughly believe
that they will make
a better future for all of us.
If we can play together,
then we can live together.