People assume that I became
a costume designer because I love fashion.
But that wasn't it at all.
My heroes were Langston Hughes,
James Baldwin, Nikki Giovanni,
Sonia Sanchez.
Playwrights, poets.
Those were the designers
that inspired me.
People think I sew,
but that's not really what I do.
What I do is I tell stories.
When I was first starting out
doing costume design for theater,
my mom came to see a play I was doing
and she came backstage afterwards.
She sat in the costume shop
while I gathered the laundry
from the play,
brought it up to the costume shop.
She said, "You mean to tell me
that you graduated with a four-year degree
to come out and do somebody's laundry?"
What is costume design?
Nobody really knows what it is
that we do.
Is it fashion? Do you sew?
I mean, they know what lighting design is,
they know what directing is.
I think as we evolved
as a filmmaking body,
there's more focus on it as an art form.
For me, costume design
is the process of taking an idea
and making it come to life.
It starts, you know, in here first
and it, is developed.
You have to understand
a little bit about people,
what makes a person who they are,
where they live, what they believe in.
Sometimes that's really reflective
on the outside.
It's storytelling.
The best costume design
does this quiet work
of setting the stage for the viewer.
When it's in the hands of someone
like Ruth Carter,
you can't even tell
that she's designing to tell a story.
There's a certain way that Ruth
assembles her costumes
that makes you feel like,
whoever this person is,
that they are indeed the...
the owners of this...
you know, I don't want to say costume,
because I think that the power is
that you don't think of it as "costume."
You think of it as, like,
"This is... this is who they are."
As a director, you wanna
surround yourself with the best people.
The films I've done with Ruth,
it's not like...
you gotta talk all the time.
Nah. We know what we're doing.
And I trust her,
knowing that she's gonna come back
to show me stuff
that's gonna be right on the money.
She makes you feel
good about yourself in those clothes.
You can tell when,
she's gotten it right or she feels like
she has it right because she lights up.
What makes Ruth's work
so beautiful is the humanity.
It never feels like costumes, you know.
It just feel like clothes.
Even when it's at its most extravagant,
people are jumping out of airplanes
and fighting big Afrofuturistic battles.
It still feels like something
that these characters put on
and that they wear.
They still felt like people.
That's one of those things when it's like,
"Man, how she do that?" You know?
The very first thing I do
is break down the script.
There is a lot of wonderment
in the first reading of the script.
"How are we going to attack this?
What is the DP going to want
as far as a color palette?
What's the director thinking of
in terms of these characters,
and what does everybody see?"
One of my favorite projects was Roots.
"We start to hear the pounding of drums.
This then becomes the screams of Africans
being taken into slavery.
The waves of the ocean sea join this mix.
Kizzy sees a figure coming towards her
for a moment.
It's clear as day
that it's young Kunta Kinte."
It's just beautifully written.
My job is the... the visual, story.
You know, to bring those textures
and those colors that,
you know, how beautifully this reads
into the story.
I think the first initial idea
is very broad.
You want the colors of the scene
to support the words
that are in the script.
The dirt, the drums, and the sea.
The blue indigo of Africa
and Kizzy's hair wrapped
in this natural homespun cloth.
You can feel the color of the earth,
whether it's red clay or brown.
You can kind of really feel the richness
of the scene.
This is like the imagination part
of the process.
The script is just the beginning.
I take that and I expound upon it.
Right now, we're in the costume shop
of our film Dolemite Is My Name,
starring Eddie Murphy.
Dolemite is the story of Rudy Ray Moore.
He was a comedian,
and he created his own pimp character
called Dolemite.
Dolemite is my name,
and fuckin' up motherfuckers is my game!
Ooh!
The '70s is such
a personal time for me.
It was when I was a teenager,
and I remember a lot of things about it.
So, I'm bringing all of that
to the costumes of the movie.
We knew
that we were going to go really bold.
All of our fabrics, and our linings,
and our buttons, and our trims.
And combine them in such a way
where it would really tell this story
of this larger-than-life character.
Then comes the nuts and bolts of,
"What do these ideas really look like?"
and "How do I place them in front of me
so that I can realize them?"
There's lots of people that need to know
what your vision is.
And so, the mood boards
help explain all of that.
It's a hodgepodge of fabric swatches,
magazine tear sheets,
illustrations and sketches,
photos from the original movie.
Anything that gives us inspiration.
Everything that Dolemite wore was custom.
I don't wanna get in my car
with this shit on.
I'm glad y'all brought my clothes to me.
This happened to be something
close to what Dolomite actually wore.
We'll never really know for sure
what that mesh was.
I'm thinking if Dolemite
were to walk in here in that suit,
he'd say, "Man, this is made
out of chain mail."
And I'd go, "What?"
But this is kind of what we used.
It's quieter than chain mail
would have been.
You know, once it's done,
it becomes a wearable garment.
And then, you get the actor in it,
it's very rewarding.
The fitting room is a transformation room.
So you're gonna be in the pimp scene,
so we've gotta get you right.
Let's see you try on this shirt
right here. This green one.
She wants you to be comfortable
in what you're wearing
while you're doing your work,
so that you can do your best work.
He's putting on his pants.
There are times I want to disappear,
and there are times I wanna be the thing
that you can't take your eyes off of.
And she gets that.
Turn around, let's see.
Ooh.
Transporting into the '70s.
When I put my costume on
and I look at myself,
then I've come to completion.
Yes! There it is.
I think that it's fascinating
how the actor and the character
kind of meld.
Yes, so now you got to stand
with some attitude.
There we go.
And that's really your job,
and that's what they want you to do.
Collar out.
Done!
I'm looking at things
and how they can be better
and how they can change.
It's like an artist on a painting.
It's never finished.
That's how I feel
about all of my costumes.
You have to see what you don't want
sometimes to know what you want.
And sometimes it's like,
"My God! Wait a minute.
Close your coat. Take your shirt out.
Take it out. Hurry up, hurry up.
How much time do I have?"
- Marker!
- Start blocking for rehearsal, guys.
It's never done.
Someone has to just, like, drag me away,
kicking and screaming,
and then they can roll the camera.
- Go ahead. Mark rolling.
- Rolling, rolling.
I really enjoy
recreating the '70s.
The '70s was my era.
Those years of high school,
I was into drama.
I just liked the performing arts a lot.
By the time I went to college,
I hung out in the theater department,
and I was acting.
I remember auditioning
for Molière, The Would-Be Gentleman,
and not making the audition.
And the instructor saying, "Do you want
to try doing the costumes?"
So I said, "Okay."
There was no specific study
in costume design,
but I knew how to navigate
around the scripts.
I went to the local fabric store,
bought a bunch of fabric,
got some patterns.
That just snowballed into the next
production after the next production.
Before long,
I was the costume designer on campus.
Theater was my first love.
Designing for theater is very different
from designing for film.
With theater, you view things
from the audience
when you're designing it.
There is a certain amount
of texture and color
and things that you don't see
the further away you get from it.
So, we make things larger than life,
patterns are sometimes bigger,
so that things that you've done
read from the audience.
But in film, because everything
is blown up so large,
things that make an impression
are sometimes extreme details.
But film was the last thing
I was really thinking about, you know.
I was really trying
to get a theater project.
In this very theater,
I was, designing the costumes
for this dance company,
and it was that show
that introduced Spike to me.
As a director,
you have to be a talent scout.
I was forming a team.
Like, I was general manager.
In sports, you know,
puttin' my team together.
So I needed a costume designer.
He sent me postcards,
inviting me to screenings
to see She's Gotta Have It.
And I was like,
"Nah, put it in the drawer.
Another one from Spike,
put it in the drawer."
Then my friend, who introduced me to him,
called me and said...
"Spike brought his film
She's Gotta Have It
to the Cannes Film Festival."
And I was like, "What?
Why didn't I answer
one of those postcards?"
Someone called me one morning
at, like, five in the morning.
He said, "Ruth." It's like, "Yeah?"
"Ruth?" "Yeah?"
- "Ruth"
- "Yeah?"
"It's the man of your dreams."
I said, "Denzel?"
"No! This is Spike."
Do The Right Thing directive was
this film takes place
on the hottest day of the summer.
Shorts, tank tops,
cut-off jeans.
I mean, even look at what Ruth
had Rosie Perez wearing
in the opening credits sequence.
All that stuff that Rosie's wearing
while she's dancing,
that's... that's Ruth Carter.
Do The Right Thing is the film
that single-handedly made
hip-hop fashion a thing.
The reds, the blacks,
the greens, the yellows,
that are really mimicking
various West African flags.
It was very prevalent in Brooklyn
to have a connection to your culture,
and to Africa,
and to wear kente shorts,
and to have necklaces
with the continent of Africa.
And we wanted to make
these African crop tops
and African shorts.
We wanted to sort of show how
pop culture responds to the inner city.
She's using
this vibrant color palette
as a color palette of protest.
That's why the costumes
in Do The Right Thing are so important,
because they help us understand
the politics of the space
that most viewers in middle America
had never really experienced.
The moment when John Savage,
wearing a Larry Bird
Boston Celtics T-shirt,
accidentally steps
on Buggin' Out's new pristine Jordans?
Yo!
That's part of the culture.
I mean, like...
Yo!
It's why that movie
still persists
as one of the most influential
films on race relations
in 20th-century America.
Hollywood wasn't used
to the Spike Lees of the world.
He wanted to show black people on camera,
in cinema,
in more of a realistic manner.
We didn't have images of ourselves
that were positive.
I grew up looking at, um,
all of those old black-and-white films.
Birth of a Nation
was one of the first films.
And it was so derogatory
towards African-Americans.
There's this white man
running around in blackface,
and this woman screaming
and running from him, like he's a beast.
And, um, you know, other movies we were
either tap dancing or serving someone.
I think the '60s
started to change that,
but it was very slow.
And we went through blaxploitation,
where we were pimps, and drug dealers,
and prostitutes.
I've got ten of the finest hoes
in the world working for me.
I'm gettin' a hundred dollars a day
from each one. Okay?
We are tasked
with the responsibility to rewrite that.
I was raised in a small town,
Springfield, Mass.
When I look around
my old childhood library,
it still feels like this place
where I can come
and just lose myself in history,
and poetry,
and just whatever it is
that I'm trying to learn about.
And the possibilities are just endless.
This library happened to be
across the street from my high school.
This was the hooky spot.
Nobody ever really questioned me
for being in here.
Even if it was two in the afternoon,
I could be in the library.
Just escaping.
We always wanted to be conscious.
So, reading about slavery
or knowing about civil rights
was an easy entry point
for me as a young person.
I like to feel like my costumes
are supporting a greater story.
The story of the times
and the story of the person.
And I like to feel
that they have a breath to them.
It was a natural progression for me
to be on films that had me research.
What were the colors of the time?
What were the economics of the time?
Once you understand the world
that a character lives in,
you can support that part of the story
with your design.
Malcolm X was the first film
that I'd done that, um,
went through so many eras.
He was so multi-faceted
with all the things
that he did in his life.
Researching New York in the '40s
was wonderful.
Harlem was alive, it was buzzing.
And so you really wanted to bring in
that sense of the heartbeat of Harlem.
There were certain areas
that were really broad.
Those were the zoot suits.
Zoot suits were considered
a hoodlum fashion.
Roseland!
The dance sequence in the film.
Those zoot suits.
That was... That was amazing.
I researched exactly
what the length of the coat was,
how narrow the pant was,
what kind of chains went around,
what kind of pocket watch,
how long the feather would be,
so that we could really get a true sense
of what a zoot suit
looked and felt like to wear.
From there, we took the journey
to his gangster days
in the '40s and the '50s.
And then we go from there
to incarceration.
I went to the Department of Correction
and I asked them
if I could see Malcolm X's files.
I had medical records,
his booking photo,
and I had quite a few letters
that he had written.
And I noticed
how his penmanship changed
and his grammar increased
as he educated himself.
When he came out of prison, he was humble.
I connected to that moment
with his costume.
He was bent over
in this rumpled, oversized suit.
He was not that cocky gangster anymore.
I feel it's a big responsibility
to dress these big iconic figures,
because people... know them.
They feel endeared to them.
You have to actually honor them
with your artistry.
Sometimes, when you watch a film,
it's supposed to represent
something real and true,
but then you kind of only get
the film version of it.
She always makes a point
to bring out the realness.
The humanitarian aspect
of her costume design,
and the meticulousness of her choices
give the person that's being depicted
this kind of dignity,
where historically, you know,
that was lacking that.
I looked at the cargo list
that was on the real Amistad,
and I saw that there were blankets
and there was cloth.
You know, I felt like these were Africans
that came from different communities.
They would maybe cover their hair,
wrap turbans.
As they arrived,
they were brought to jail.
We managed to keep the American flag
kind of wrapped on one of the guys' heads,
as if he's unaware of what that means.
And in one of the writings
of the Amistad case,
it said that in the courtroom,
they looked like doves.
And so, I gave them all
these clean white shirts
to sort of give them
that dove-like appearance.
You know, I don't like to rely
on what my subconscious tells me
because I think it's usually wrong.
I love these, runaway slave ads.
Ten-dollar reward for Tabitha.
"Tabitha is about
five feet two or three inches high,
dark yellow complexion, stout made,
common head of hair,
and about 20 years of age."
I like the people that I read about.
And I really want to see them
resurrected in some ways.
So, I work really hard to try
to get those details on, an actor.
I think that there hasn't been enough
study of African-American history.
And the way that we tell the stories
sometimes is through movies.
And it's important
that we take responsibility for it and...
and, um...
bring to life, as best we can, the truth.
There's eight of us in my family.
I'm the youngest.
- Roy was three years older than me.
- Yeah. I was working.
I used to go in your room
and you used to hate that.
- Yeah.
- Why?
I still don't know why, to this day, Roy,
why you hated me in your room.
Because it was my stuff.
Ma, what kind of kid was I?
- A nice daughter.
- ! I'm glad.
Ma used to drive us all to school,
and then you'd drive up the hill
to Springfield Technical Community College
and go to your class.
I was puttin'...
I was puttin' emphasis on education then.
I wish I could have went to school
a little longer. I like...
I like school.
The thing I believe that my mom
instilled in me is this empathy,
this great empathy for people.
You know, because of the psychology
that my mom studied
and brought home every day,
I got to take a deep dive
into why people are the way they are.
You know, I'm grateful for her
for teaching us that empathy.
That's probably why I see
the things I see in characters.
This is the old machine
that was in my room.
By day, it was a desk,
and, by night, I guess,
it was a sewing machine.
It had a cool light.
I also, when I left, I guess, for school,
I wrote a sign.
So, while I was away,
nobody would get rid of it. I...
I was endeared to this machine.
It says, "This machine belongs
to Ruth E. Carter.
Do not throw it away, sell it, or keep it.
Thank you. It's mine."
I remember I sewed
a big, fluffy, orange vest
that I wore to one of my friends' parties.
And she asked me, you know,
"Did you make that?"
And I said, "Yeah.
I made it."
I had a knack for creating stuff
out of nothing.
Going from junior high school
to high school,
I decided I wanted to be a Muslim.
So, I took my pants and I opened them up
and I made 'em into long skirts,
and I covered my hair.
And I started studying the Koran.
And people thought I was deep, you know?
I'd do the little praying to the east,
and people gave me a little distance,
because I had a purpose and I had an aura.
Eleventh grade,
it all went out the window.
I went to the other school
that was up the street.
I just remember going to this new
high school with this totally new look.
High boots, and long gauchos, and a vest,
and blouses, and a briefcase.
I remember a couple of kids in the hallway
asking me if I was, like,
a substitute teacher.
You know, I was no longer the Muslim girl.
I was the... you know, the businesswoman.
And then, that way,
I put on these personas.
When we try on clothes in a store,
we get excited
because they're brand new and fresh.
You walk out of the store
with your new item in your shopping bag,
and then you get home and you're like,
"What was I thinking?
This doesn't look at all like who I am."
Or, "I feel silly."
You're really talking about character.
One of the ways I get ideas
is to go out into the street
and observe people.
Especially when I'm in New York.
I just love to go people-watching.
I look at people's clothes,
how they carry themselves,
and I make up stories in my head
about their lives,
and it's all based on what I see.
These are the people
that bring the ideas to my work.
Clothing can tell you so much
about a person.
You know, if they're a mother,
or if they're an artist.
That informs you
about what their footwear looks like.
The age of their clothes.
The expense of their clothes.
What's their economic status?
What do they care about?
All those things work out
on the clothes.
It's part of a bigger picture.
Maybe if we take a little bit less
of the research
and, kind of create our own lines
down the sides there.
Once I have my ideas,
I'll do a rough sketch
and I'll take my ideas over
to a digital illustrator.
I think it needs to have
a little bit of a train.
- Okay.
- We should probably add a train to it.
If we get a little bit more dramatic there
and then add some more
of the elements of the shield.
It's up to you to kind of inform them
about detail.
That's the great part,
because they're really wonderful artists.
And they make you look really good.
It's a very
collaborative process
in which we're able to work,
but also back up the designer
to figure out what's going on
in... in their head,
and try and get it out
to everybody else.
- Which is, an art form all in itself.
- Yeah.
Are you trying to say
that there's a lot in my head?
Yeah.
- And I got to get it out of there.
- Yeah. I help. I help.
A lot.
Beauty is a subjective thing.
I need it to look like
what I'm feeling in my soul.
And when it doesn't feel that way,
we have to change it.
For us, as artists, we have to create this
into a design that's wearable.
It's wearable art.
You have to be able to foresee
what the problems could possibly be
with the materials that you chose.
It can be really scary,
because time is money
and you don't want to go down
the wrong road.
There's so many details to the vision.
And the bigger the project,
the more challenging it gets.
Any time you have to create a world,
it's a huge, monumental task.
When people say,
"Wow, she designed the Black Panther.
Tell me how your process is."
I'm like, "Yeah! I go home
and cry in my pillow every night
because I'm scared."
I think it was because of the level
of stress, the level of responsibility.
You know, I hadn't done
a superhero film before.
In a film like Panther,
it's as complex as it can get.
But, I'm a football player. Man, like,
you know, I came up playing football.
We would call somebody like Ruth...
um, like, we said they had
good footwork.
Kind of light-footed. Know what I mean?
Like, she's able to transition in ways
that it's almost seamless. You know?
Before the Black Panther,
I had small exercises in fantasy
and futuristic ideas.
And one thing that I did
o research what would be the future
was to look at the past.
Which is what I also did
with Black Panther,
looking at the ancient indigenous tribes
around Africa.
And Africa being
this vast resource of artistic ideas,
it's kind of fun
to sort of reimagine things.
Clothing, you know,
it's a form of expression.
When you see people in a film,
that's the first thing, usually,
that you get out of them,
it's what they're wearing.
You're not thinkin' about it.
You're waitin' for them to talk
or for them to do a action
that's gonna tell you something
about them.
But... but, you know,
that first impression
is what they have on.
When you meet Killmonger in this film,
you know, as soon as you see him,
you get a little bit of a read.
Good morning.
He's wearing western clothing.
He's got the denim jacket on
with the black...
It feels contemporary,
of the moment. Um...
You kind of clocking all those things.
And I think when it's...
when it's working at its best,
you know, costume is... is...
is giving you information
about the character
in a way that serves as a story.
When can we get this done?
You can pick any fabric
and they'll make up anything
that you want.
African fabrics are actually brought
to Africa by the Dutch.
And since we were trying to imagine
Wakanda before it was colonized,
we tried to create
our own patterns and things.
And then, I mixed in a lot of this,
so, for the color and...
You know, this says Africa.
So, regardless, it does say Africa.
But I was very careful
about where I used it.
These are from Mali, the Tuareg.
These are mostly, like,
around South Africa, the amber.
They use a lot of it.
We came to places like this
to purchase a lot of pieces we used
in the Warrior Falls.
A big theme for me was
his concept of what it means to be African
and how colonization has affected that.
You know, we wanted to really define
the ethnic groups of Wakanda.
You know, and kind of
steep them in real...
you know, real ethnic groups
from the continent.
The Dora Milaje
was the fan favorite.
There were so many things
in that costume
that had significance to Africa
and to creating them as the highest
ranking female fighting force of Wakanda.
The printing of their bodysuit
has this special raised print
to look like scarification.
Their neck rings and arm rings were taken
from the Ndebele tribe of South Africa.
And the overall color of red
was taken from the Maasai
and many other tribes of Africa.
On the tabard,
there are small, trinkets.
And these trinkets represented
what tribe they hailed from.
I kind of added that,
so that each of the Dora
would have something
that individualized them.
You want it to feel real.
You want it to portray a certain amount
of dignity and cultural specificity.
And some of it, you're pulling
from real people that exist in the world,
and other bits of it,
you're kind of totally inventing.
We were able to infuse
cultural and African diaspora
with the realm of fantasy and future,
and keep it within the realm
of what the fans knew about Black Panther.
And we needed, like...
We, the black folks,
needed a movie like that
where there were black heroes.
It's still kind of, you know, inspiring,
especially for young kids.
The Black Panther stands alongside
many films that were addressing
those issues of dispelling
negative stereotypes
and moving the culture forward.
As much as I love being a designer,
there are sacrifices
that come along with it.
You are traveling three months
in one city,
and then you're back in another.
And so, it's really hard to cultivate
long-standing relationships.
I met my husband in a hair salon.
Mario Jackson.
Snag was his nickname.
His street name.
When I first met my husband,
I didn't know he had gang affiliations.
He was charming, he was witty,
he was funny.
He was a regular guy,
but, you know, he grew up in the Crips.
And as an adult, it's something
that just kind of never leaves you.
On Baby Boy,
he told me everything.
Some nice shoes.
How they would wear
the Stacy Adams,
how they would crease their pants,
what type of Wrangler jeans would be worn,
how the T-shirt would fit at the neck,
what sizes I should buy,
what kinds of belts I should buy,
what a Romeo was,
where I should go and buy them.
All of those terms were defined for me
right there in my own house.
You know, it wasn't easy
being married to Snag.
He didn't invite that world into our home,
um, but he did, keep
an active group of friends
that came from there
that he knew all of his life.
That day, he was going out
to meet some friends.
I remember standing in the driveway
as he was leaving,
and then he stopped
before he got in the car
and he came back up the driveway
and he gave me a kiss,
and then he drove off.
That was the last time I saw him.
That day, I went and got a canvas.
I was going to paint in the backyard.
I saw this picture of this woman
with her hands outstretched, looking up.
I started painting this canvas
and just kind of getting into the subject.
It was, like, ten o'clock at night,
and I thought,
"Well, yeah, I haven't heard from him."
Someone called me
and they said, "Ruth."
And the way they said, "Ruth," I...
kind of knew.
They were watching a boxing match
in a respectable bar.
Remaining undefeated...
And the guy came in,
he pulled a gun out,
killed my husband's best friend,
and then shot my husband seven times.
Basically, out of jealousy,
because he had changed his life
and moved on.
My feet just weighed a ton.
My feet were like cinder blocks.
I could barely pick my feet up
to walk in there.
I know it sounds strange,
but after that happened
and he was freed,
it freed me, too.
And I didn't have the weight
of his life anymore.
You know, that's when life began
for me again.
I had been searching
for a spiritual practice.
Going to church never connected.
Doing meditation just wasn't enough.
And then, Oprah was on set one day.
We were in the middle of Louisiana,
in the bayou,
way out somewhere.
And she just said,
"You know, art is prayer.
It's just God speaking through you."
And that just hit me like a ton of bricks.
Because I was like, "Wow!
Did she just say art is prayer? Like...
I can totally see that."
When you zone out
on something that you're working on,
it's creative,
it's imaginative,
it's restorative.
Why wouldn't it be prayer?
I'm gonna take me seriously.
Now.
I have taken school,
parents, friends, poets seriously.
I've known the cracker
to be seriously dangerous.
I've taken daytime,
nighttime rhetoric seriously,
and been wounded by lovers
of slick, black rapping.
I'm gonna look in a mirror
each time I pass one
and smile at my image, sayin',
"Yeah, sister, it ain't easy,
but move beautifully on past it.
Keep holdin' your head higher,
'cause your best is yet to come."
I'm gonna take me seriously.
Today. Now.
And study myself.
Get a PhD in Ruth Carter
and dare anyone
to be an authority on me.
'Cause I'll be wounded with Ruth's beauty,
learning,
love,
and will be dangerous.
I'm gonna be serious about me
and live.
Yeah.
There's a little bit of a dust
on his...
right there on his shoulder.
So, you might want to help her,
because the collar is a little off center.
Okay, let's... let's move on
to the trench coats.
How are we gonna do that?
Black Panther put everything
that I've ever done on a pedestal.
And I think that's really nice,
to be able to re-introduce your work.
Just look at it as a body of work, now.
This is the first time I've ever seen
all those costumes together in one room.
This is great. This is really great.
A lot of great, great memories here.
A lot of really, really important work.
And a lot of great times
with a lot of great people.
It's very interesting that people
are just now kind of catching on to Ruth.
Her work has this presence of, like,
"My God!" Like...
You mean, like, one of those Picasso type
of... You know what I mean? Like it's...
Her legacy’s, like,
so, so much bigger than she is.
We've seen this woman,
over the course of her career,
learn how to bring that humanity,
that emotionality
to life through her clothes
in a way that is
not only historically accurate,
but that can imagine possibilities
for black lives
that the history books
have told us wasn't possible.
We go to the movies
to be entertained
and to be educated in some ways.
So, it's a big part of our culture. It...
It stamps our place in time.
If I am tasked
with this great responsibility
of dressing a culture,
I want to spur it even further
than people have done in the past.
I am so overwhelmed with joy.
Ladies and gentlemen, we made it.
Can you believe
this night is finally here?
When I look back,
I see a little bit of a different me
with each film.
It feels like I am here.
That I have connected to...
my voice.