[director] Is this going to be
a slapstick comedy? Is it an action film?
You know, let's have fun with it.
-Yeah.
-We can do anything.
Oh yeah, nice.
So what do you think your movie should be?
All right, it should be like
the documentary version of Inception.
[Bjarke] The whole premise
of Inception is that, in real life,
you can't really realize the dreams
because you have so many constraints,
but whereas in the dream world,
they could do all these kinds of things.
And when architecture is at its best,
that's exactly what you're doing,
you're coming up with
something that is pure fiction.
Then after all the hard work,
all the permits,
all the budgeting
and all the construction,
it now becomes concrete reality.
[Martinussen] When Bjarke came around,
Danish architecture was somehow sleeping.
We had our heydays back
in the '50s, the '60s, the '70s.
We became world-famous compared to
how small we are, actually.
At the time Bjarke came around,
people didn't expect
anything really to happen.
And I think you could argue
that he really made everybody wake up.
[dramatic music playing]
What he was proposing had such a scale
and such revolutionary qualities
that the Danes got scared.
[news reporter 1] Bjarke Ingels
is having his moment.
[news reporter 2] At just 40 years old,
he has established himself
as one of the world's most inventive
and sought-after architects.
[news reporter 3]
His designs can be provocative.
[commentator] He's transforming
the shape of New York as we know it.
[dramatic music continues]
[Bjarke] There's no doubt that
in architecture there's this catch-22.
Nobody will entrust you
to build a building
until you've already built a building.
This is the Maritime Youth House
in Copenhagen.
It's...
I guess it's our first building.
I celebrated my 30th birthday
in that space.
It was just completed.
Our practice, Bjarke Ingels Group,
or in short BIG,
started 15 or 16 years ago.
Our rise has sort of coincided with
the rise of the environmental movement.
So we came up with this idea
of Hedonistic Sustainability.
What if sustainability could be part of
actually increasing your quality of life?
So I think in this case, it's a
beautiful site, but the site was polluted,
because they had been painting
the underside of boats here.
A lot of the money in the budget
was reserved for digging up the topsoil...
and moving it somewhere else.
So we thought, what if we covered
the entire ground with a wooden deck?
Then we can leave the soil as it is.
We put up this sheet.
If you want more program over here,
we'll just lift the deck here.
If you want to park some boats here,
we store the boats underneath the...
So I think it had
this sense of possibility.
These rolling hills next to the sea,
it also somehow inspires
movement and playfulness.
We won the competition
for the Maritime Youth House.
We found a lot of ways
to solve the problems
in a completely unproblematic way.
Even though it's a very small building,
with a small budget,
I think it had an impact,
and it won a handful of awards.
And I think it showed
that even something that is essentially
like a hut for boy scouts,
which is typically more like
a barrack building,
like sort of off the shelf,
almost like a trailer,
that's what it normally is,
and with the same resources you could get
something that was completely different.
I think that definitely opened people's
way of thinking about architecture,
what a building could be
and what it could do.
[director] So what happened this week?
[Bjarke] Me and my partner here,
at the New York office, Thomas,
went to London to Kensington Gardens,
next to the Serpentine Lake.
For the last 15 years,
the Serpentine Gallery--
they have been making a pavilion,
the Serpentine Pavilion.
So, in the middle of Hyde Park
over the summer,
from June to end of October.
The Serpentine Gallery
is almost like an icon
for miniature architectural manifestos.
It's always commissioned to an architect
that has never built in England before.
And today, two thirds of the people
that design these pavilions...
are Pritzker Prize-winning architects.
They're really at the top of their game.
For a comedian, it's like performing
at Saturday Night Live or...
It's a stage where the history
of the people that have performed there
makes it an honor in itself.
And we met with
the co-directors of the Serpentine
and they started the meeting
by telling us that the good news was
that we would be designing
this year's Serpentine Pavilion.
I guess that was Tuesday
and today is Friday.
Without having any sort of design in mind,
imagine this sort of logic
where you have some kind of undulation,
so it almost like looks
like a marble curtain,
and that's what gives it stability.
Almost like a James Turrell.
That you're inside this weird translucent,
undulating slice of marble
and then you're looking up through...
I think with the dome...
I mean, it creates that one experience
of being inside,
and it's probably a beautiful optic
from the outside,
but that's only that one use.
You're doing an entire building
within six months.
Normally a project that goes fast
takes six years,
so we're going to try to see
how many ideas we can crank out.
I mean, there was something interesting
about like making a wall
that morphs to become a pavilion.
You know, it could be a way
of making a wall
that creates a cave,
and an auditorium, right?
[Thomas] Yeah.
It's more like a magical manipulation
of a conventional element...
[Thomas] Mm-hmm.
that then becomes space.
Cool?
[in Danish] Let's do it!
I'm Elisabet Ingels.
And I'm Knud Bundgaard Jensen.
And this is Fidel. He's a Bichon Havanese.
And it's Bjarke
who had given him the name.
-He's from Cuba.
-Cuba.
We couldn't call him Cuba,
because there's a Cuba down the street.
Another dog.
Yeah another dog, and so it's Fidel.
[Knud] He was drawing very much.
It was his great interest.
He was considering making comics
until 18, 19 years.
[director] What did you think
when he told you he was
gonna study architecture?
-Actually--
-It's a family project.
-Yes--
-[director] So explain.
We told Bjarke,
"You can later try making comics,
you can later get a job
at an advertising bureau,
but I think that you should
study architecture."
[Bjarke] I went to Architecture school
in Barcelona.
I wanted to use some of the first years
where you get some basic education
in drawing to become a better cartoonist.
You end up in the school,
you want to figure this thing out.
So I went through this sort of
intellectual, serial-monogamy,
falling in love with one architect.
then the next, and next...
And it completely warped my idea
of what architecture could be.
And that was definitely the year where
I became the person I am today.
Getting out of Copenhagen, living in
another city, speaking another language.
And finally, dropping out of school,
starting my own company in Barcelona
with some friends.
It was also clear that when I returned
to Copenhagen a year later,
with sort of a Spanish suntan,
I was a completely different person
and could somehow do things
and be credible making statements
that would have been unimaginable
the year before.
[Bjarke on video] The qualities of
the spaces and the indoor climate
doesn't come from the machine room,
but from the qualities
integrated into the architecture.
Rather than architecture
without architects,
it's sort of engineering without engines,
or Functionalism 2.0.
We started our company
without any clients.
But after a very long and winding road,
we finally ended up building a building.
The VM House.
My name is Per Høpfner. I am a developer.
I meet Bjarke, first time in 2001.
He said, "We are a new company,
architect company,
we are so fucking good,
and we are very creative,
and we are so bright,
and we can build very, very cheap."
"Okay, how cheap?"
"Oh, you can't imagine."
Immediately, I like him.
[upbeat music playing]
[Høpfner] And at that time,
there was nothing here in this area.
And if you should attract people,
it should be very cheap,
and there could be something special.
[Bjarke] We designed
these buildings for pioneers.
We got permission
to make the apartments 30% deeper,
and we made sure that each apartment
had a double-height space.
For every three floors,
there was only one central corridor,
so that, instead of having a corridor
at every level that you had to pay for,
we boiled it down to every third level,
so we could get great efficiencies.
The beautiful thing is that at this point,
we hadn't built as much as a dog house.
[Høpfner]
And the day we started to sell here,
we have sold 110 flats for one Sunday.
[Bjarke] It created a lot of noise.
[Høpfner] And I can tell you one thing.
A lot of his colleagues,
they don't like him.
And they don't like him because
they've been so successful abroad.
It's not usual for a Danish
architect company to make money.
[Bjarke] We were definitely seen as being
alien in a sort of Danish context.
And it is a culture where difference,
or disagreement is almost embarrassing.
How's it going?
-[woman] Hello, happy New Year!
-[Bjarke] Happy New Year!
You never left the office?
[all laugh]
Yeah.
[speaking Danish]
[Bjarke] Because the time schedule
is so compressed
for the Serpentine Pavilion,
we have to make decisions absurdly fast.
We have been keeping
a series of ideas alive.
For a while we had three,
then we boiled it down to two.
And I think we are looking
at this idea of a wall
that is made out of
fiberglass bricks or blocks.
And then you're almost pulling it apart,
like a zipper,
so that it becomes undulating landscapes
on the exterior,
like a valley and a hillside.
And then on the inside, it creates
this crevasse, or canyon, or cave.
So try to place this...
-[colleague 1] This one is lower.
-[colleague 2] That one should fit, yeah.
That's kind of nice.
[Bjarke] There's no doubt that the wall
looks very good, right?
[colleagues] Yeah.
[Bjarke] And it feels very comfortable.
It's the kind of shit we do.
And I think it's also
the one we have developed the furthest.
There's a couple different ways
we can put it together.
I have a feeling that we could do this
and it would be a great success.
Yeah.
There's almost nothing
that wouldn't be cool about it.
Maybe we should just do it.
[all laugh]
[Bjarke] The way you realize
your wildest dreams
is actually one step at a time.
[fast-paced music]
The master plan of this whole neighborhood
was basically saying to build
a stack of apartments
and then a big box of parking behind.
So we got this idea:
What if the parking fills the entire site?
And then instead of having
a vertical stack of homes,
they become houses with gardens,
like a giant staircase covering
a big sort of mountain of parking.
What we see here
is all the sun-facing gardens,
where each home has a garden
that is roughly the same size
as the apartment itself.
And then they sit on
this cave full of cars.
The underside actually becomes
the front door of the homes
of people arriving
so we made the underside
very, very colorful.
Whenever we design homes,
I'm also thinking about myself:
What would I think would be amazing?
And I think in this case,
it's almost like realizing a dream
that an apartment block doesn't have to
look like a big, boxy slab.
It could be like
this sort of man-made mountain.
You don't have to choose
between building a parking structure
or an apartment building.
You don't have to choose
between a house with a garden
or having a penthouse view.
You can actually have both.
And once you force these sort of seemingly
mutually exclusive concepts together,
you actually get a new hybrid
that somehow ends up looking different
because it performs differently.
I think The Mountain is
a quite good example of pragmatic utopia
in the sense that it's done
within one city block,
so it becomes a very pragmatic realization
of something utopian
but, like, one block at a time.
When I think
just that The Mountain is here,
it means that there is another way,
there is another possibility.
And therefore
it makes the utopia more possible.
And that's what we mean with Yes Is More.
At that point,
I'd never really written it down,
so it existed in the form of lectures,
verbal tradition.
[inaudible dialogue]
Yes Is More is presented
in the form of a comic book.
It's not like you have the text first,
and then you get the pictures.
You have the things intertwined
so it becomes more conversational.
So then of course, in retrospect,
it feels quite logical,
because I wanted
to become a graphic novelist
and I kind of deviated
from that trajectory at some point,
it's kind of a return to home.
[Martinussen] The book very rapidly
gave him the position as a rising star.
He was... Suddenly, he was there.
And quite massive.
Which changed
the culture of young architects.
Bjarke took up the idea of, I think,
asking the Danes:
what is it actually that we want to do
from having had
this spectacular tradition?
How can we be revolutionary,
but in such a manner that you would not
forget your tradition?
So for instance, the building
that we are standing in right now
is actually a building which is,
in itself, a merger.
[Bjarke] The 8 House.
[digital music plays]
500 homes, shops and offices
and kindergartens.
Classic apartments and more town houses.
And we've actually created
a giant mountain path
with an ADA-accessible slope.
So it sort of becomes like
a three-dimensional community.
I like big ideas and the BIG Group
when it makes a big building,
that's just for me.
[laughs]
We feel like we are living in a village.
We have the beautiful rooms in common
where we make parties and eat together,
and a path that you can walk.
The children out here,
they really enjoy it,
and I can see it from our balcony.
It's just beautiful to see.
[Bjarke] In the big picture,
architecture is the art and science
of creating the framework of our lives.
And the buildings that we built,
they either open possibilities
or they hinder encounters or connections.
With the 8 House, it really has become
a three-dimensional community
and you can see it
in the people living here.
There are so many initiatives,
a lot of the people know each other.
[in French] Gabrielle? How's it going?
[laughs]
[in French] Is that beautiful Hélène?
[Gabrielle] Good to see you!
[both laugh]
Actually the funny thing is Gabrielle
and I and her husband were doing...
I think you were both
students at the time.
-Yeah.
-Or--
-Interns, yes.
-Interns.
So we were working on
our first book and exhibition,
so we were doing sort of
24-hour work days--
-Yeah, Yes Is More!
-for a month and a half.
So we ended up resulting in this
amazing comic book and exhibition,
but also I think
that was actually the time
when we suddenly noticed that
they were hanging out more and more,
even after the deadline was over.
Exactly.
Yeah, so Hélène is a little bit part
of BIG as well, yeah.
For sure.
And one of the smallest BIGsters. Okay.
[Rice] Bjarke started off doing
sort of affordable housing.
And he was so young, by the standards
of a world-renowned architect,
that he had to go from being
a scrappy, young architect
to a large-scale, almost corporate firm.
And he's had to ramp that up
very, very quickly.
[Bjarke] Some of the criticisms have been
that our buildings are too cheap,
but that's because, honestly,
they have been cheap buildings.
But somehow we manage to
turn that into architecture
that actually points in new directions,
opens up new possibilities,
but in a field where
there is almost zero innovation.
The Maritime Museum,
is our first museum.
That has found much more universal praise
simply because it's a museum
and therefore it came with the budgets
where you can do a little bit more.
[Rice] He wants to do everything.
He wants to build 1,000-foot skyscrapers,
I think he wants to build,
you know, museums,
I think he wants to build
football stadiums.
The issue is he doesn't feel
that he needs to make a choice.
[church bell rings]
[piano music playing]
[Høpfner] Danes hate big scales.
But Bjarke brought in the big scale.
And they were very skeptic
and, I would say, quite hateful.
[Knud] There were one or two old
professors at the School of Architecture
that were very skeptical and critical.
It is easy to understand
if you consider how young he was.
[Høpfner] He never follows the rules.
And a lot of my fellow developers said,
"Per, how can you build with this guy?"
[Bjarke] Whenever we talk
about architecture,
and whenever people have
opinions about architecture,
the most typical argument is:
something is bad
because it doesn't fit in.
[piano music continues]
And maybe in Copenhagen,
if you would look out,
you would think that it's red brick
and red tiles.
Six stories, end of story, pitched roof.
But when you think about the things
that people really associate
with Copenhagen,
that the Copenhageners think
are unique to their city,
they always think about
those historical spires.
If everybody followed the rules,
Copenhagen wouldn't look like Copenhagen.
And I think it's going to be interesting
to see, like how...
what's going to happen
with Danish architecture,
but, of course, we also kind of migrated
to America.
[upbeat music playing]
The city is an experiment and Manhattan
is the perfect example of that.
It's about accommodating diversity.
And after five years at BIG,
we were in a pretty good spot,
but New York felt like
it could be a real adventure.
[Knud] It was a great opportunity.
He needed more space
because he wanted
to make big architecture.
[Bjarke] Things that evolved
in one context
suddenly find their true potential
when they move into another context.
To begin with such a big canvas
like a city block
on the waterfront of Manhattan,
this is a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity,
we cannot mess it up.
The Courtscraper is this hybrid
of an American skyscraper
and a Copenhagen courtyard.
[Martinussen] When you get into
that league, everything changes.
New York is the city of the world,
so it can't get more wild.
[Bjarke] There was
a certain energy and pioneering
and maybe I just felt like
feeling that energy again.
The Royal Parks are our landlords
and this is their beautiful park
and they stipulate that the architecture
cannot come
within three meters of the tree.
Now that of course
is not a problem in principle,
but it is a problem in practice.
So the question is,
is this three meters?
This is like, one, two, three.
In my mind, we can nudge it.
-I think we can nudge it a meter over.
-You think a whole meter?
Yeah.
So you need another meter?
I think if we just--
And then we don't take it
a meter away from the fence?
Take it a meter away from the fence
and move it closer to the signature line.
But the other thing
that I am seriously curious about
is actually when you're standing here
and you imagine that you would
basically take the two yellow outlines
and literally flip them,
and I think we simply turn the other way.
-And then we move it--
-So it comes out...
It grazes the path
and then the entire hill is gonna be
in the sun, which is also nice.
-Perfect, lovely.
-That could be nice, it's so exciting.
[Bjarke] The Serpentine, right now,
is massively under construction.
Fiberline, the company
that makes the boxes,
is plowing ahead and is shipping
the first shipment to go to London.
Obviously we don't have
any wiggle room from the beginning.
So we're now finding ways to catch up.
The beauty of it
is you can take a single material,
a single technique, a single idea,
and you can make very clear statements,
undiluted by those thousands
of constraints and compromises
and negotiations, which take so long.
Over the last 15 years,
we've completed 12 or 13 buildings.
But right now,
we have 17 construction sites.
Right where this new green promenade
touches downtown,
it's going to create a new urban oasis,
which is going to become
our new neighborhood.
[inspirational music playing]
In our work, Yes Is More.
We try to come up with this
inclusive approach to architecture,
of getting everybody's input
to the extreme,
where suddenly it becomes
the driving force.
We're not gonna stop
until we have incorporated
every single concern, no matter how small.
[inspirational music continues]
This obsession
about making everybody happy
becomes a recipe for making
something that is really extraordinary,
because it has to perform
in so many different ways.
These buildings become like
interesting scales in your own life.
You have to ask yourself:
is this going to be worth
the next seven years of my life?
And if you're not realizing a dream,
then seven years is a really long time.
[man in Danish] Some things are missing.
That's one thing.
There are things
that aren't placed right, either.
[Bjarke in Danish]
How wrongly are they placed?
[man]
It touches, so that there isn't room...
-[Bjarke] Oh, funny.
-Look.
[Rice in English] Is he doing
too many projects at once?
Is he spread too thin?
If you're the architect who says yes
to everything, including every commission,
do you, at some point,
have to start making compromises
in your vision?
Do you start repeating yourself?
[podcast host 1] Should we take a look
at what some people think of Bjarke?
[podcast host 2] Let's hear it.
[podcast host 1] "BIG's projects
all repeat similar traits:
stacked, banal glass volumes
with roof gardens,
cheaply made for developer satisfaction."
Another comment is:
"BIG sucks. My nine-year-old
does more interesting shit in Minecraft."
[Rice] The issue is he can
sort of freely take
from all sorts of aesthetic traditions
and create things that are
aesthetic promiscuity.
In that he can, to put it crassly,
market in a way that's
elegant, innovative and fun.
[Bjarke] If you go beyond indifferent,
you will awaken a response
in both extremes, right?
Especially in the age of the internet.
If you read the comments on blogs
as if they are valid criticisms,
then you're going to have a rough time.
I really grew a thick skin.
When you're doing something like this,
even though it's carefully crafted,
and premeditated and discussed
and designed and tested,
when you see it,
it has to feel effortless.
-[man in Danish] This is the bar.
-That's the bar?
[man] So these gratings
are going in afterwards.
[Bjarke] The bar up there, right?
It will be quite cool with the gratings.
[laughs]
[Bjarke in English]
All the things that end up
becoming the values
that somehow define you
are all the things you take for granted,
right?
I grew up in a tiny house
with a giant garden.
It's not my self-image
to be an environmentalist
and it's not my self-image
to be a social activist.
But you can't see the forest
for all the trees.
This is due west.
So the sun actually sets, and that means
that the last 30 minutes before it's gone,
or let's say an hour,
you have two shadows
on the walls in the back
because the sun is there above the trees,
and it's also right there below the wheat.
And both suns throw shadows,
so you have this amazing moment
where the sky has two suns.
Or at least the view has two suns,
which is quite nice.
And then actually another funny thing,
in the winter, the water freezes.
And suddenly the lake,
which was normally the end of the garden,
became this public square
where every single kid,
touching on the lake from all sides,
would come and ice skate.
So just like this interesting idea
that maybe just the seasonality of things,
or that suddenly something
that was a barrier became a meeting point.
What changes over time
is that naïveté fades away,
but it's replaced by another kind
of confidence
that will make you better
at seizing the moment
and grasping what's important.
Okay, let's-- let's sit down.
[director] Doc, anything else?
My mom has made, like, 500 meatballs.
[laughs]
-[knocks]
-[dog barks]
[Knud in Danish]
Do we have microphones on?
[Bjarke in Danish] Yes, but I don't think
they will use them.
[Knud]
Can't you ask him to shut up?
[all laugh]
[Bjarke] Oh, Fidel.
Can you shut the fuck up, dear Fidel?
[Bjarke in English] There's a sense
it's hard to make it in your own village,
but if you go to the big city
and make it there,
then, "Ah, it's one of us. He did it."
I think we also changed
people's mindset of what's possible,
so I think Copenhageners
got used to more crazy ideas,
so when we actually presented
the idea of putting a giant ski slope
on the roof of a power plant,
I think it was in an environment
that we had already influenced
a little bit over the last decade,
so that it was receptive
to that kind of thinking.
We felt that we could propose
something seemingly insane
and actually get away with it.
Copenhill.
A waste-to-energy power plant that has
a giant public park on the roof
where you can ski.
It's the tallest and biggest building
in Copenhagen.
It's, again, this idea
of environmental thinking,
that if you have a power plant
that is so clean
that you only have a little bit of CO2
and a little bit of steam coming out
of the chimney, but no toxins,
you literally have clean mountain air.
And instead of having to be
far away from it, you can enjoy it.
[in Danish] It's quite amazing
that this will be the children's hill.
It begins all the way up there!
[builder 1 in Danish] It's high up,
even though it's the children's hill.
[builder 2 in Danish] Yeah, that's right.
It's too cool!
[Bjarke in English] Of course you can say
you put an Alpine ski slope
on the roof of a building.
It's a building, it's not a mountain.
I think, to my relief, it feels
much more like being on a mountainside
than being on a roof.
This is around 130 feet
and the top is 300.
The elevator arrives there
so that when you come out,
you have almost like a flat area here.
And then you sort of...
Then you just take off.
I think a project like this can be
sort of a beacon in showing the world...
clean tech presents
almost utopian possibilities.
And I think the Steam Ring
is a powerful symbol of exactly that.
The chimney, instead of being
a symbol of pollution,
it becomes a celebration.
We've worked with Realities United
to design the chimney
so that it puffs rings of steam.
And it's also like somehow, like,
when you start this kind of journey,
it's, like, you know
what's important for you...
but you don't necessarily know
where you're going.
But you know that,
if you make the decision
based on these things
that you know matter to you,
wherever you're gonna end up,
it's where you need to go.
Of course, I couldn't have predicted this
when we did this,
but they're definitely
sort of a similar spirit.
[director] Where's the Maritime
Youth House from here?
It's basically like...
You can see it
where the trees are, exactly.
And then you can see...
the Mountain and the VM are right there.
[director] What about the chapel?
That's right there.
This is probably
the most spectacular toilet experience
you can get in Copenhagen at this point.
[laughs]
You can take things
that are considered infrastructure:
highways, bridges, power plants...
and crossbreed it,
so that it actually has positive
social and environmental side effects,
like the power plant.
Those combinations are very powerful
because it's taking a very strong force,
which is necessity, utility,
and giving it poetry and possibility.
There's something there
that can be taken much further.
-[photographers chattering]
-[cameras clicking]
[Peyton-Jones] For Bjarke to have
achieved this incredible prominence
at 41 years old
is nothing short of extraordinary.
Because in order to do that,
an architect has to have built.
[Bjarke] There is this kick of seeing
a completely novel thing come to life.
[clapping]
Thank you.
It is such a tremendous honor to play
in the middle of a royal park,
and especially since
it's the Serpentine Pavilion...
[director] Are you surprised
by how far your son's gone?
And how quickly he's done it?
Yes. Frankly speaking,
we had not expected that.
[laughs]
It's... special.
We live in a time
where we need to pull all disciplines
to address the big questions
of the 21st century.
And Bjarke never really shied away
from really addressing topics
which are found beyond architecture.
[Bjarke] I am longing to discover things
that I hadn't even thought about.
There's this real genuine moment
of immaculate inception,
where you're sort of...
"This is brilliant.
I never thought about this before.
This would be amazing. It's beautiful."
And two seconds after,
you can't think of the world without
thinking of this being a part of it.
[piano music playing]
From Tribeca, it will appear like
a vertical village of singular buildings,
each tailored
to their individual activities,
stacked on top of each other,
forming parks and plazas in the sky.
[piano music continues]
[Bjarke] I like this idea
about architecture being a way
to manifest your dreams
into the real world.
It's almost like a shaman
with brick and mortar.
That is the true power
that we as humans have.
We actually have such a massive
impact on our environment.
So now that we have this power,
we can either use it to create a nightmare
or we can use it to realize our dreams.
And, of course,
the latter is much more interesting.
[director] Do you dream of buildings?
I never dream about my work, actually,
interestingly enough.
[director] There goes the end
of the documentary.
[Bjarke laughs]
[director] Cut!
[upbeat music playing]